<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mynde of the godly and excellent lerned man M. Ihon Caluyne what a faithfull man, whiche is instructe in the worde of God, ought to do, dwellinge amongest the papistes.</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1842</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22831116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22831116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1789:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mynde of the godly and excellent lerned man M. Ihon Caluyne what a faithfull man, whiche is instructe in the worde of God, ought to do, dwellinge amongest the papistes.</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>R. G.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[151] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By me Ihon Oswen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Ippyswiche :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. D. XLVIII [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: For the faithfull amongest papistes.</note>
                  <note>"Translated by R.G."--P. [149].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁸ K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:1"/>
            <p>The Mynde of the Godly and excellent ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned man M. Ihon Caluyne, what a Faithfull man, whiche is inſtructe in the Worde of God, ought to do, dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linge amongeſt the Papiſtes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>☞What felowſhip hath righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes with vnrighteouſnes? What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hath light w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> darkenes? How a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth Chriſte with Belial? Or what parte hathe the beleuer with the infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele? &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini M.D.XLVIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sathan was loſed oute of the botom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les pyt,<note place="margin">Apoc. 20.</note> and (for mans vnthank<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes towarde God for his manifolde benefytes) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted to range through out the whole worlde, to deceyue mankynde, man off hym ſelfe naturally prone vnto euyll, &amp; therfore readie to enclyne to his diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycall ſuggeſtions and temptations / wel nygh all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole worlde (a fewe of the lytle flocke of Chriſt onely excepte,<note place="margin">Gene. viij</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hathe pleaſed God of his mercie ſo to preſerue, as he alwayes doth his church that they haue not bowed their knees to Baal) hath neglected and ſet naught by Goddes euerlaſtynge teſtament &amp; goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which is the power of god in to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation <note place="margin">3. Reg. 19.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:3"/>
to all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue. And wheare as they knewe there was a god, &amp; haue not worſhipped him as god, nor thanked hym, but became vayne in their ymagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and theyr foolyſhe herte was blynded, when they counted them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues wyſe, they became fooles: and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the glorie of the incorruptible God into the ſymylitude of a corruptible ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. Wherfore God, likewiſe, gaue them vp vnto their hertes luſtes into vnclean<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, to defyle their owne bodies in them ſelues, which turned the truthe of god in to a lie, ſo that they worſhipped &amp; ſerued the creature more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creator, which is bleſſed for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1</note>And what more enſued Sainct Paul declareth, They Iuſtlie receyued the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde of their erroure, and as they had no regarde to knowe God, euen ſo god gaue them vp vnto a lewde mynd, to do thoſe thynges whiche were not comelie beyng full of all vnrightuouſnes whore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, wickednes, couetouſnes, malyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, full of enuye, murther, ſtryfe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, euell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicioned, whiſperers, backe biters, diſpiſers of god, doers of wronge
<pb facs="tcp:25772:3"/>
proude, boaſters, bringers vp of euyll thinges, diſobedyent to their elders, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oute vnderſtanding, couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t breakers, vnlouing, ſtubburne, vnmercifull, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with all kynde of wyckednes.</p>
            <p>Thus doeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſee (good Chriſtian rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) howe daungerous a thynge it is, to neglect or diſpyſe the myghtie worde of god, againſt whiche (notwithſtanding) the gates of hell can not preuayle: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in diſpiſynge or reſyſtinge it althoughe of a malycious or peruerſe mynde, thou goeſt aboute to ſuppreſſe &amp; kepe it backe thou doſt nothing els but procure thine owne dampnation, the worde of god flo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſſhinge neuertheles: for as the goſpell is ſaluation, to them that beleue it, ſo is it dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that beleue it not. This dothe Chriſte verifie and affirme him ſelfe, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ihon. 12.</note> he that refuſeth me and receyueth not my wordes, hath one all ready that iudgeth hym.</p>
            <p>The worde whiche I haue ſpoken, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall iudge hym at the latter daye: for he ſhall haue nothynge to cloke his ſynne wythall.<note place="margin">Ihon. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Paraduenture we wyll thynke that
<pb facs="tcp:25772:4"/>
Saynct Paul doth ſpeake thoſe thinges onelye of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were before his dayes and ſo perſwade our ſelues that it was nothinge meant of vs, but in leſſe then we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue our ſelues not giltie in thoſe and lyke offences that they in the olde lawe were plaged and puniſſhed for, let vs not perſwade our ſelues to be cleare of lyke threatenynges. No, let vs loke for none other thinge, but to be caſte vp of god into a reprobate and leude mynd and ſo headlonge into all fylthynes and iniquitie the iuſte rewarde of our errour whoſe ende is death euerlaſtynge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. viij.</note>God fed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelytes with fyne Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na ſente them from aboue, they abhorred it &amp; wiſſhed to be at their full groſſe fleaſh pottes agayne in Egipte.<note place="margin">Exo. 16.</note> They were plaged for their vnthankefulnes. God hath ſente vs the true Manna,<note place="margin">Ioh. vi</note> his euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge word y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread of lyfe we abhor it, we can not abyde it, we wolde be at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> full pottes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> groſſe fleſſhe of mennes traditions to poyſon our ſelues. Well, ſhall we thinke to eſcape gods wrathe? Is god become a chaungelyng? will he not punyſſhe vs, for our vnthankefulnes
<pb facs="tcp:25772:4"/>
as he dyd them? yea trulie. For we be more worthy of puniſhment then they, ſeing we haue their puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">Num. xi.</note> for an en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſample before our eyes to beware by.</p>
            <p>God alſo brought the children of Iſrael out of Egipt by wonderfull miracle,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> for when it was vnpoſſible by all reaſon, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other they ſhoulde haue bene deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troyed by Pharao and his armye being behynde them: or elſe to haue bene all drowned in the rede ſea before them: the mightie power of god cauſed the deepe ſea to ſtande on eyther ſyde of them like a wall ſo that they paſſed through it ſafe lie, but theyr enemyes purſuinge them were drowned horſe and man. Wheare as they ought with whole herte &amp; mind continually duringe their lyues to haue geuen thankes vnto that myghtie god alone for their deliueraunce: they ſhortly after made them a golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calfe,<note place="margin">Exo. 32</note> fell down and worſhiped it, offering ſacrifyce vnto it, ſaying. Theſe be thy goddes (O Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell) whiche haue brought the out of the lande of Egypte. This their vnthankful Idolatry Moyſes called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt ſinne and was greuouſly punyſſhed: for there
<pb facs="tcp:25772:5"/>
enſued murder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of xxiij.m. Now if it can be proued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue ſhewd no ſuch vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward god, haue not reſiſted his word nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted no ſuch lyke offence: then may we ſleape the more careles and feare no ſuche plages to fall vpon vs, for of thys we may be ſure, God will not punyſſhe vs without a cauſe. But amongeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other thinges, what ſay you to thys, I pray you? We were longe in Egypte that is in the bondage and captiuitie of Pharao the deuyll, and when we could be delyuered by no power no merite or interceſſion of any creature beſyde chriſt viſyble or inuiſible / mortal or immortall / &amp; wher as it was impoſſible to al reaſon, but other we ſhoulde be euerlaſtinglye drowned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> red fiery ſea of hell &amp; death being allwaies before our eyes: or els to be deuoured of the furiouſe Pharao the deuyll purſuinge vs: God of his mere mercye (aboue all our deſert) ſente hys onely begotten ſonne Chriſte Ieſus, to become verie man and dye for vs, for in as moch as we had committed ſuche of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> as was forbidden in paine of deth
<pb facs="tcp:25772:5"/>
we muſte nedes be redeamed agayn by death, and that by ſuche a one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhoulde not remayne dead ſtyll, for then ſhoulde not he ouercome death but death ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hym: therfore muſte he ryſe again and ſo by death ouercome death.</p>
            <p>This parte hath chriſt played alone. He died for our redemption,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 1. Cor. 1 Ephe. 1</note> he roſe againe for our iuſtification &amp; ſo ouercame death ſynne and hell: and thus moſte wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully delyuered vs out of euerlaſtynge thraldom and captiuite. But haue we alwayes aſcribed the renowne and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of our redemption and forgeueneſſe of ſynnes to god alone? No no but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to maſſes ſatyſfactorie with ſondry other vayne traditions of man. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do we attribute, or whom do we prayſe for our daylie preſeruation from perilles and Ieoperdyes? God alone? No, our manyfeſte actes do openly reproue vs. How many men and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue bene, when they haue bene in daunger / ſome of drowninge, ſome of burninge, ſome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reakynge their neckes, and ſome lyeng ſo ſycke that to all reaſon they ſemed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>rable, that, yf god of his goodnes pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb facs="tcp:25772:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them and rayſed them vp agayn, wold ſhortly after get them to one ydol or other (to whom thei had vowed their pilgrimage and offeringe) as ſome to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ladie of Walſyngham ſome to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Grace, or vnto ſome other foule ydoll. And where as they ſhoulde haue geuen glorie and praiſe to the one euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng god, which alone delyuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue kneeled downe in the ſight of the whole multitude &amp; thanked a dome ymage, worſhippyng and offering their ydolatrous ſacrifice vnto it. Was not this ydolatry worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worſhipping of the golden calfe? yes trulie. For then ſacrifice was commaunded to be offered to god with calues, but not calues to be worſhipped: as for ydolatrous ymages were forbydden then as they be nowe. And for that the people might be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more allured to lyke abhomynation y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes taught them for their owne aduauntage to come onely in their ſhirtes &amp; ſmockes what was this els but to ſay with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelytes? Theſe be thi goddes (o Iſrael) whiche haue brought the out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande of Egipte &amp; bondage: yea and no doubt
<pb facs="tcp:25772:6"/>
the worlde bothe hath and ſhall be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as greuous plages as they were, yf it do not earneſtly repent and forſake not onely ſuche abhomination: but alſo all kynde of ydolatrie that is, all inward or outwarde worſhipping of the ymage of any thinge viſyble or inviſyble: or ſea kyng forgeuenes of ſynnes or ſaluation at any creature mortall or immortal, but only at gods mercy, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for chriſtes ſake.</p>
            <p>More ouer for theſe and ſuche lyke our vnthankefulnes and offences, God had iuſtly geuen vs vp into ſuch a lewde and reprobate mynde, that all we (a few excepte) were not onely geuen headlong into all kynde of vyce and ydolatrie: but were ſo ferre gone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we were iuſte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the curſe pronounced out off goddes mouthe by the prophete Eſaie.<note place="margin">Eſai. 5</note> wo be to you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> call euyl good, and good euyll, makyng derkenes lyght and light derkenes, takynge bitternes for ſwetnes and ſwetnes for bytternes. In this caſe were we. That whiche was vyce and ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>homination, we toke for godlynes and vertue: And that whiche was godlynes and vertue in dede, we toke for hereſie &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25772:7"/>
ſynne: for who was he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thought it not godly to profeſſe him ſelf into an abbey frier houſe or nonry? Who was he that ſpake againſt them, and that with gods worde but he ſhoulde be hated and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted? Who was he that thought but that it was hyghlie meritorious to go on pylgrimage to this or that ymage? Who was he that coulde ſpeake againſt them but he ſhould be in daunger of his life? Who durſt ſpeake againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes hote purgatorie, but that he ſhoulde be burned to aſſhes? And as for the abuſing of the lordes ſupper whiche they called the ſacrament of the Aultare, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpake but a worde againſt it, or againſte their wycked maſſes ſatiſfactorie (thoughe it were the verie ſcripture) hangynge was to good for hym, he muſt dye moſt cruel death. But thankes be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall god for he (to the declaration of his glorie &amp; for his electes ſake) hath ſtyrred vp men as his inſtrumentes to ſpeake, write and printe myghtelie againſt ſuche abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and he hathe turned the hartes and powers of ſome chriſten Princes a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt them to ſuppreſſe them and roote
<pb facs="tcp:25772:7"/>
out all ſuche plantes as our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath not planted.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Finally, ſeing that papiſticall abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynations and ydolatries be now well nyghe all knowen though they be yet ſcarcely halfe lefte in many places, it is requiſite and highly neceſſarie to know how a faithfull chriſtian man, endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirite of god &amp; truely taught in hys worde, ſhall behaue hymſelfe amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtes, were in and how ferre he may be conuerſaunt with them: namely, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he may be preſent at their maſſe and ſuperſticious Ceremonies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out offence in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he, although by owtwarde geſtures as by cappynge and kneelynge ſeme to worſhippe with them, doth notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge in his herte worſhippe the onely lyuynge god: whether he may lawfully vſe ſuche diſſimulation or not? For thy full erudition &amp; learnyng in this behalfe although veri few writers haue touched this poincte (namely in the Englyſſhe tongue) here haſte thou (good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) this notable work of M. Ihon Caluyn a man of good learnynge and godlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, now firſte tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glyſſhe:
<pb facs="tcp:25772:8"/>
which, if thou, dilygentlie reade peruſe and marke with ſobernes, it wyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fullie ſatiſfy thy mynde in this behalfe wher as certen places in ſcripture (afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome mennes myndes) ſeme to beare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch diſſymulation in worſhipping thou ſhalte haue them moſte manyfeſtly ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the: ſo that thou ſhalt perfectly knowe, that all that be of Chriſt oughte not onely to confeſſe God with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte inwardly, but alſo (after the councell of Saincte Paule) to confeſſe the lyuinge god with the mouthe and glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie hym in their bodyes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſynge him in all their outwarde geſture and behauiour.<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 1. Cor. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:8"/>
            <head>How a faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full man ſhall behaue him ſelfe, dwellinge amongeſt the Papiſtes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any do aſke me Counſell oftentymes, how they ſhuld behaue them ſelues amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtes where it is not lawful for them to worſhyppe God puerly: but euery man is conſtrained to vſe many cerimonies whych haue bene inuented againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god, and be full of ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now it were not very hard to anſwere them in this matter &amp; to defyne vnto them ſymply y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth therof, yf they were fully
<pb facs="tcp:25772:9"/>
determyned in their hertes to folow wholy and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all that God hath com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded them by his worde. But I wote not how the moſte parte of men, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue knowen a thing diſpleaſith god do neuertheleſſe gyue them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues leaue, and alſo do defende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues againſte it. For there haue bene dyuers haue aſked me counſell in this matter eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogether after ſuche a faſhion as Baalam did of god, when he wolde go vnto kynge Balach,<note place="margin">Nume. 22.</note> for he knew well ynoughe that it was againſt the wyll of God that he ſhoulde take that viage vpon hym, but yet neuertheles he ceaſed not to aſke him leaue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Euen likewiſe theſe men here being in maner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict
<pb facs="tcp:25772:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in their conſcyence / that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll done, to bowe them ſelues before Idolles / do enquire and demaunde what they may do not for to captyuat &amp; make ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte their aſſent vnto god, and reſte vpon his worde / but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intente men ſhoulde geue them the bridle: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hauynge anſwere after their deſire may quyet them ſelues in their vice through vayne flaterie. To be ſhort euen as the prophet Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell ſaith.<note place="margin">Ezechi. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> They go ſekyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſhould make them cuſſhens to lay their conſcience a ſleape vpon and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſhould make them beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they lyue when they be in deathe.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe bycauſe it is our office puerly to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verite, I can not diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:25772:10"/>
nor refraine, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I muſte nedes ſpeak thoſe thinges whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I think neceſſary to be kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen: ſpecially when I am requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red ther vnto, but for as muche as all the difficultye cometh of this, that we do euer giue more hede to kepe vs in the fauoure of the world, then to pleaſe god I exhorte euery faithful perſon in the name of Ieſu Chriſt / for to reſiſt his owne affections, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye be obediente vnto the will of his maſter Chriſt. It is a paynefull thinge for a man to put him ſelf in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of loſing both body &amp; gooddes / to ſtere vp all the worlde againſt him, to lyue in opprobrye and vtter reprofe, and to leaue the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, where one may lyue well at eaſe, for to go into a ſtrange cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey
<pb facs="tcp:25772:10"/>
as one goeth aſtray. I do graunt it to be ſo, but what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte leſſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould learne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcole of Ieſus Chriſte, but to forſake our ſelues, but if ther be any ſo weake or frayle that they can not at the fyrſte deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine veri wel what they ought to do, at the leaſt I deſire them that they wyll not flatter them ſelues ſekynge ſtertyng holes and vayne excuſes for to hyde them with / but theſe ſtertynge holes can not delyuer them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iudgement of god, yea and we ſe that this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng and as it were the fyrſte degre of the ruyne of ſuche as do fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grace of god. And when they ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not ſure for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make them ſelues knowen before men, that they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true
<pb facs="tcp:25772:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſeruantes of god duly to honor him they excuſe them ſelues &amp; wil be counted for righteous &amp; fauteles when they do with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men defyle them ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyuers kyndes of Idolatrye. Then afterwarde they percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can not this waye eſcape al maner of ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they think they be diſcharged if thei do hyde their criſtianite al togi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther without ſpeaking ſo moch as one worde of God except it be to their chief frendes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyars and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhut vp in a cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre ſuerly. Now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiles they ſuffere the truthe of God to be blaſphemed, &amp; what diſhonour ſoeuer me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do vſe to do to Ieſu Chriſt: they do not onely make no reſyſtence to the contrarie, but alſo make as though they
<pb facs="tcp:25772:11"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented to it, hauinge none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges in their mynde but to take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhuld perceyue that they be criſtians at the laſte what happeneth to ſuch maner of people which wil with ſo carnall pretence (that is to ſaye, by peruerſe ſubtilitie) begyle both god and the world god ſuffereth them to fall as it were into a depthe of darknes depriuing them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledg that he had geuen them, and ſo finally y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuylles poſſeſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſtyrred them vp againſte the goſpell and maketh them perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cute with a hoote &amp; cruell furie, the doctrine whiche before thei knewe to be of god, and that by good right, for it is reaſon, that that man which turneth the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytie of god into a lye for to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye
<pb facs="tcp:25772:12"/>
hym ſelfe in hys iniquitie, ſhoulde therfore fele ſuche ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geance. For as moche then as as infirmyte doth let vs for to accomplyſſhe our deutie, let vs rather gyue all glory vnto god in confeſſing our myſerye, then by inuentynge cauillations and ſtartynge holes to bring vpon our ſelues ſhame &amp; double dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation, for we ſhoulde take the enſamples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> punyſhementes of god for admonitions or war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynges, to the intente that we ſhoulde learne to walke in hys feare.</p>
            <p>What ſhal men do then? firſt of all let vs not meaſure oure duetie due vnto God after our owne commodite, for after that maner we ſhall neuer attayne to the truthe. Then afterward
<pb facs="tcp:25772:12"/>
let vs not in this matter haue reſpect vnto our owne perſons for to ſeke oute that whiche is moſt conuenient for vs after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe. Thirdely let vs not take counſell at oure owne brayne, which waye is beſt to wynd vs out of parell and trouble: but let vs rather truſt in the proui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence of god nothing doubting but that he is able inough for to kepe vs euen in the myddes of a thouſand deathes, if neceſſite required, that it ſhoulde come ther vnto: thus doing we ſhuld not haue any nede long to ſtand in aduiſement or diſpute of the one parte or of the other parte whyther we ſhould w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trouble with the loſſe of our goodes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the daunger of our lyfe, obaye vnto god or no, &amp; for to pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:25772:13"/>
hym gette the euyll wyll of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but hauyng ones hys commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demente, we ſhoulde redelye &amp; withoute doubte folowe it as a ſuer waye commyttynge vnto hym what ſoeuer myght come therof &amp; gyue our ſelues ouer vnto hys holy ſauegarde: here haue we y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely mean wherby to gouerne vs truely. In this caſe I wil recite a godly exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple that Sainct auguſtyne doth re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herſe whyche ſhall be good for to bolde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and incorage vs thus for to do. It is that Sainct Cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prian after that he was conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to the deathe bycauſe he wold not do ſacrifice vnto ydol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les was moued and inticed to condiſcende vnto the ſame for ſauyng of his lyfe. And ſpecialy the Iudge coueting to delyuer
<pb facs="tcp:25772:13"/>
hym required hym inſtauntly, for to do ſo and prayed him wel to bethynke &amp; aduyſe him ſelfe. Vnto whome he gaue a ſhorte anſwere, that in a thing ſo holy deliberacion myghte haue no place. Let vs now conſyder in what eſtate Sainct Cypriane was then, he ſawe the death be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore his eyes: but for aſmoche as he was at a point with him ſelfe, for to folowe the comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of God, the ſame dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered him frome all perplexite, that he was not aſtonyed: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dyd not bowe or change his mynde, but abode inuincible.</p>
            <p>This is then a notable ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which ought to be well printed in our memory, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we do not attempte throughe any deuelyſh preſumption, for
<pb facs="tcp:25772:14"/>
to aduyſe oure ſelues whether we maye do that whiche God hath ſpoken or no: as thoughe we might controlle him, but yf we will take counſell at oure owne head &amp; turne away from his worde, let vs ſurely wayte for the curſe which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounced by the Prophet Eſay, vpon all them which gyue not auctorite vnto his ſpirite for to rule in their counſelles and axe not at his mouth to take there at their determinacions.</p>
            <p>We ſe nowe touchinge this preſent matter, that yf our lord hath on this wyſe declared his will, we contentinge our ſelues with his worde, may haue ſure knowledge of that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought to do. This nowe concluded, yf anye man will ſtill to it replye,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:14"/>
let him go and pleade agaynſte God, to ſe whether he can wyn his proceſſe againſt one ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a partye ſpecially hauinge ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll a matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, let vs remember that Ieſus Chriſt doth learne vs al this leſſon at the firſt entrance into his ſcole, that yf we be aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med of him or of his worde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men,<note place="margin">Mat. 10</note> of vs will he be aſſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med whan he ſhall come in Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie with his angelles.</p>
            <p>Beholde then how that our Lorde is not content when we do knowledge him ſecretly one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and in our hertes, but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth ſtraightly, that we doo declare before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by outward profeſſion that we be of his: &amp; he dothe not accept vs to be of his kyngdome but vnder that
<pb facs="tcp:25772:15"/>
condicion. And it is no maruell for that that ſainct Paul ſaithe can not be falſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> that as with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart a man beleueth vnto right wyſnes: ſo muſt he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe with his mouth that he maye be ſafe Whereby he ſignifieth that can not be the fruyte of faith before God, which bringeth forthe no confeſſion before men. Who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer nowe draweth backe, he muſt go ſeke him a new maſter.</p>
            <p>Now one wil demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther euerye one muſte declare him ſelfe openly or no, yf he will doo his dutie thoughe no man enquire of him his faith? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it is not my meaning for in aſmoche as it is a particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar office to preache openlye / it is not conuenient that euerye man medle therewith / no ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:25772:15"/>
were it expedient nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient? I meane not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euery man ſhoulde go into the pulpet to declare their chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte / or elles that we ſhuld pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſh it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtretes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blowing of a trompet: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerye one after their vocation in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he is called to take hede that he geue god his glory.</p>
            <p>Now for as moche as oure lorde hath not determyned nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the tyme nor the place, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther yet the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, how farre we ſhall go, we can not make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certayne lawes therfore.</p>
            <p>But it is mete that euery one (to his power) doo applye him ſelfe faithfully, to doo the ſame by all the meanes that he can, conſydering alwayes the ſtate in whiche he is and the grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
god hath geuen hym, &amp; bycauſe that we be al ſlouthfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent, except that we haue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes ſome ſpoure for to ſtere and pricke vs forth, let vs haue theſe godly ſentences printed in our hartes wherin it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to be ready to ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der a reaſon of the hope that is in vs vnto eueri one that axeth vs.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.</note>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 2</note> In lyke wyſe wheare it is ſayd that thoffice of euery faith full perſon is, to take his neygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arme and ſaye let vs aſcende into the hyll of Syon in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of Iacob and he wyll teache vs to walke in his waies, we ſe now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhould be ſuche zeale in vs both for to exalte the kyngdome of God and alſo for to edifie our neyghbour: and that we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:25772:16"/>
geue all our ſtrength and apply all our ſtudy to do the ſame.</p>
            <p>But for as moch as we haue no certeyne rule to certifye vs, how far &amp; how wide we ſhould walke, there is no more to do then, but euery man to deſyre our lorde to directe him in true wiſdome: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may iudge what is moſte expedient to be done. And then afterwarde after his power (accordinge to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the vnderſtanding whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he hathe) he do ſeke all the meanes and occaſyons that is poſſible for to fulfyll his dutie: to the intente that we haue all wayes the folowinge of Ieſus Chriſt for our marke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68</note> of whom it is ſpoken that the zeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of god conſumed hym, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, he was inflamed with
<pb facs="tcp:25772:17"/>
ſuch loue and affection to build and interteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of god that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame was euen as a bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge fire in his herte whiche did neuer let him reſte. On the other ſide, let vs note wel, what is ſpoken of them which durſte not confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt after that they beleued in hym.<note place="margin">Ihon. 12.</note> It is that they loued more the glory of men then the glorie of god. Is it not a curſed and an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twarte choyſe to preferre men before god? Let vs take heade that we come not into ſuche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempnation.</p>
            <p>But the thing which I haue taken chiefly to handell at this tyme, is to knowe whether a Chriſtian man being rightly in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtructe in the truthe of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, when he is among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes
<pb facs="tcp:25772:17"/>
do offende god or not yf he do as other do in going to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, worſhipping of ymages, reliques, &amp; vſyng ſuch lyke ceri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies. And to preuent the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome, we entreat not now of this difficultie, whether it be euyl done to diſſemble: but whether a man may feine and counterfaicte or faſſhion hym ſelfe againſt the verite &amp; truth. A man doth diſſemble when he hydeth that that is with in his herte: but he feyneth or ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleth whan he feineth him ſelfe to be that he is not, in concluſion loke what it is to lie with the mouth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame is to feine in the dede.</p>
            <p>Now to defyne this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt note, that as there be two maner of honours that we owe vnto God, that is to ſaye,
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:18"/>
ſpirituall ſeruyce of the harte &amp; the external or outwarde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppinge: euen ſo on the other ſyde, be there two kindes of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, the fyrſte is whan a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through a falſe fantaſy whiche he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued in his hart or ſpirite doth corrupt &amp; peruert y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual ſalues of one only god The other is whan a man (for what cauſe ſo euer it be) dothe geue or tranſfer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honor which belongeth vnto god onely, vnto any creature. As for an enſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vnto an ymage, let vs then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn to ſpeake of the duty which we owe towarde god, to ſerue hym duelye. Is it ſufficient for euery man to holde god within hym ſelfe within hys harte for his ſauyour and worſhyp hym in ſecrete? No, he requyrethe
<pb facs="tcp:25772:18"/>
more of vs ſaying, that we muſt glorify him as well in our body as in our ſpirite &amp; he adioyneth the cauſe. Becauſe that both of them belonge vnto hym. Now although we had not this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, yet it is euydent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhoulde be ſo, for in as much as our bodyes be redemed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt. What reaſon is it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde proſtytute it before an Idoll? Seing that it is the temple of the holy goſt. What an horrible ſynne were it then for to defyle it with ſuch ſacryledge? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge that it is predeſtinate to receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowne of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talite and to be partaker of the glory of god, is it then conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for to corrupte and to foil it with ſuch fylth? let vs learne
<pb facs="tcp:25772:19"/>
then that euen as our ſoules be conſecrated vnto God, euen ſo ought our bodyes to be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnto his honour. S. Paul cryinge agaynſte whoredome vſeth this argument.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> Seing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our bodies are the membres of Chriſt, is it lawfull to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the membres of an harlot? By the ſame reaſon maye we ſaye, ſeinge that our bodyes be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres of Chriſt, ſhall we deuyde them frome his communion by pollutinge them and bowing of them before Idoles? Therfore our Lorde ſpeaketh of his true ſeruauntes, and geueth them this marke that they had not bowed their knees before Baal nor yet hadde kiſſed his hande,<note place="margin">3. Kyn. 19.</note> who might haue ſaid that they were not corrupt with falſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:19"/>
holding Baal for their God in their hartes. But he willinge to ſygnifye that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter lyeth not all togyther ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſayde. That they had not done him any reuerence by any owtwarde geſture. In this diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cription dothe he ſhew vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought narowly to abſtein from ſuche defylinge of our ſelues, yf that we wyll be of the nombre of his people. This is alſo that he ſaith, by Eſay.<note place="margin">Eſai. 45.</note> I am the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng god euery knee ſhall bow before me / &amp; euery tongue ſhall ſwere by my name, he declareth by theſe wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he rekeneth not hym ſelfe to be worſhypped truly, but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der vnto hym onely yea euen with outewarde geſture: and that he be worſhypped of the bodye
<pb facs="tcp:25772:20"/>
as well as of the ſoule. Nowe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the contrary is done, that is to ſaye, when one knelethe downe before an ymage, it is de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogation to his maieſte. And what wyll we more? Haue we not an expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement whiche forbyddeth vs to geue any honour vnto ymages? For the wordes whych y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord vſeth do not onely importe, that men ſhoulde not attribute vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his glorye through any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions or peruerſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but they do alſo comprehende all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men may do on what wyſe or for what ende ſo euer it be.</p>
            <p>Then it is nowe a vayne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, &amp; that dothe not elles but aggrauate and enlarge the ſyn to allege that god is content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:20"/>
thy herte: for we ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary. Euen ſo is it to allege that ydo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry procedeth of ſuperſtition and therfore that it is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted but whan the herte is there with it, for although a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do mocke an Idoll in his harte when he maketh as though he worſhypped hym: yet is he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles gyltye of this ſynne in that he giueth the honour of god to a creature / but let vs ſet a parte all ſuperſtition: what is it that a man can pretend in his behalfe? He wyll denye that he ſinneth, for aſmoch as his mind or intente is not euyll. What thyng ſoeuer (wyll he ſay) that other men do, I worſhyp the ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng god in my herte, I know that it is ſacrilege and abhomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation for a man to goo to an
<pb facs="tcp:25772:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Image, of it to ſeke or wayt for any helpe or elſe to do it any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. It is to god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I direct my ſelfe, althoughe I ſeeme to worſhyp the Image. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cloke and colour whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthyans pretended when Sainct Paule reproued them of this vice,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> for they went vnto the brotherhodes whiche men made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour of ydolles and dyd eate of their ſacrifices w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other: was this now thorow ſuperſtition? No for S. Paule bringeth forthe this excuſe in their name or perſon: we know that the Idoll is nothinge, but vanite: what folyſſhe fanſie ſo e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the worlde haue of it, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is but one onely god and one onely lorde Ieſus Chriſte. But is he contente with thys?
<pb facs="tcp:25772:21"/>
Noo. Euen cleane contrary he anſwereth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all this is nothing ſeinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through their exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples they did entiſe other to worſhip Idolles. A weake perſon (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeth you, thinketh he not that you haue the Idol in ſome eſtimation? Now vpon this is he confyrmed to do in like caſe: yea but you haue a right vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandyng in your herte. Muſte he therfore for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt died peryſſhe in bearynge hym ſelfe bond of your knowledg? Doth he not through this anſweare ſhake of all their clokes? Wyth which many now a daies wold helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. And yet doth he ſpeake more ſharpely a lytle after.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> That euen as he whyche is partaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of god is partaker of the true ſacrifice
<pb facs="tcp:25772:22"/>
ſo he which doth communicate wyth ſuche faulty and defyled maner of doinges is polluted &amp; defyled, it is a vayn thing (ſaith he) to replye, that the ymage is nothynge and that it can do nothinge. Let vs be contente that in as much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnbeleuer doth ſacrifyce vnto Deuylles / who ſo haue any thynge to do wyth them in this acte gyueth hym ſelfe to the deuyll in lyke wiſe. Now can no man be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the lordes table &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuylles togyther: neyther yet drinke of the lordes cuppe and alſo intermedle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuilles cuppe: who ſo euer doth take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one doth clearely renounce the other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Daniel. iij.</note>And in dede yf Danielles companyons myght haue ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:25772:22"/>
by this ſubtiltie, it was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foly and raſhenes for theym willingly to offer theym ſelues vnto deathe. Mighte not they haue agreed within theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to ſaye. Other men do wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippe the Image, but our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ſhalbe erected vp to heauen to worſhyp the lyuinge God.</p>
            <p>Thus the cauſe ſtandynge for to auoyde daunger, let vs be in the company of other, fayninge as thoughe we folowed them, Coulde ſuche cauillation quyte them before God? Euery man will ſaye naye, Well what ſhall we ſaye then, ſhal we accuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an vndiſcrete zeale / becauſe that they had rather ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be caſt into a burnyng fornace then to counterfaite or feyne, and haue their hartes ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertheles
<pb facs="tcp:25772:23"/>
alwayes vnto God? But this were aſmoche as to reproue the holy ghoſte whiche prayſeth them for this their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, Some man will ſaye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man can not be ſo conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſtedfaſte. Well foloweth it therfore vpon that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde not folowe thexemple which is ſet before vs for a doctrine.</p>
            <p>Euen accordynge as we do ſeke ſterting holes for to excuſe our ſyn: ſo ſemeth it vnto ſome men, that they haue a good ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucion for this texte: when they ſaye, that it ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of the Idolatry of the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then, and therfore it ought not to be applyed vnto our tyme.</p>
            <p>For the Paynims (ſaye they) were not onely deceyued in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge
<pb facs="tcp:25772:23"/>
of peruerſe ceremonies: but alſo in as moch as they had Goddes deuyſed &amp; forged oute of their fantaſye. It is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell then (ſay they) yf our lord do ſo greatly reproue their ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of doinges: but this is not all one with that that is done amonge the Papiſtes: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe the ſeruice of God be amonge them corrupt and fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet alwayes their intention is none other but to worſhippe God. To be ſhorte, they arme them ſelues with this diuerſite that they thinke there is not ſo greate parell to be partaker in any Idolatry the which is coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red with the name of God, as in an other that were altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withoute anye couer. But vnto this I anſwere that for aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moche
<pb facs="tcp:25772:24"/>
as the worlde goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to ſerue God after a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and an vnlawfull maner, that then it doth worſhip an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole: what cloke ſo euer they make. Then, they that inuente ſuperſtitions whiche God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth and refuſeth, mighte very well ſay, we will ſerue god but in aſmoche as God accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not ſuche ſeruice they do it rather to the deuyll.<note place="margin">Rom. 1</note> Wherfore ſainct Paule ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which did tranſforme the glory of god into any corruptible figure, did ſerue the creature and not the creator. But to thintent a man maye vnderſtande more playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, how feble this defence is, let vs take thexamples of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture conuenient vnto this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.<note place="margin">Nume. 21.</note> Marke the braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb facs="tcp:25772:24"/>
whiche was not inuented raſhely by the folyſhnes of men but by the will of God. It was not onely a memoriall of the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefyte which God had done to the people of Iſrael, but alſo an holy Sacrament of Ieſus criſt Afterwarde dyd they make of it an abhominable Idole, &amp; yet neuertheles, this was not done without a Godly ſhewe or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the name of God. I de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde now yf that any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame tyme had made as thoughe he had worſhypped it for to faſhion him ſelfe vnto the ſuperſtition of the people, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we wold excuſe him? I thynke there is no man that wolde not condempne him.<note place="margin">Exod. 32</note>
            </p>
            <p>Loke alſo vppon the golden Calfe whiche Aaron dyd caſte,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:25"/>
was not the ſame to repreſente the lyuinge God? for when he made proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſhulde aſſemble togither for to kepe the feaſte of the Lorde whiche had brought them oute of the lande of Egypte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame was receyued of euery man w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out contradiction: it was then a Ceremonye ſet vp to honour God with. But becauſe it was falſe and peruerſe, it was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Idolatrye. He that had feyned him ſelfe there to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente excuſinge him ſelfe by the tytle of God / hadde he therfore bene gyltleſſe? We wolde all of vs condempne him. How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it then in a lyke matter, we will not ſeme to erre. As moche maye we ſaye of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues which Ieroboam prepared <note place="margin">3. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 12</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:25"/>
for he profeſſed not to bringe in any new God: but rather prote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted that he wold always hold hym vnto the lyuing god. And in dede he had none other reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte then to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goinge to Ieruſalem, for feare leaſte they ſhoulde ioyne them ſelues agayn vnto the houſe of Dauid. This was notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge ydolatry, bycauſe he inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted a ſtrange maner of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynge againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god. yf that any man now whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented not vnto this abhomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation had ſacrificed there, had he done well? And without ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng any more a do. Reade we that any ſeruante of god did at any tyme worſhippe there? No but contrarywyſe we reade y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lorde by hys Prophetes
<pb facs="tcp:25772:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
forbad it as a cryme very abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynable.</p>
            <p>Now to make an end of this artycle the temple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaynes, was it builded vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Iupiter or Mars? We knowe that it was done to the name of the lord god of Iſrael, was it therfore lawfull for any faithfull man to worſhip there. It is very playne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it had byn an extreme abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude then vpon theſe reaſons inuincyble, that it is no more le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full to communicate in an ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry which is decked with the name of God then if it were all together the ſacrifice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p>Nowe, before we paſſe any further, in as moch as we haue now ſene that ydolatry, yea, all
<pb facs="tcp:25772:26"/>
although it be committed but fainedly, doth alwayes diſpleſe God: it is conuenient for vs to applye this doctrine vnto our tyme. If a man were amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turkes, there were no doubt but he ſhould do wickedly and agaynſt god, to enter with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into their ſinagoge / ther for to kepe their ſuperſtition? And yf there myght be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d paraduen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture any man ſo far paſt ſhame as for to aproue this, he ſhould declare himſelf to haue no fear of god nor any conſcience of ſin. A good cauſe whye? For loke euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhippyng of god done in the churche or in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the faythfull after hys word is a ſolempne acknowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge that we do holde and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte him for our god: and that
<pb facs="tcp:25772:27"/>
we do honor hym openly. So a man to ioyne him ſelfe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turkes or Paynims for to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their maner of worſhiping that they vſe (which is naught) It is a kynde of forſakynge of god, by which he is defiled and accurſed. To ſay ſo moche of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtes, plainly it ſemeth a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſtraunge thing. For we haue many thinges with them to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon together: &amp; what ſoeuer deuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or variance there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene them and vs, yet muſte we (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out all compariſon) haue more felowſhyp with them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the heathen, yea, and yf it were but for the honour of the name of Ieſus Chriſte whiche they beare: in which thing alſo we agre with them.</p>
            <p>We muſte ſee then where in
<pb facs="tcp:25772:27"/>
and how farre, it is lawfull for a chriſtian man that is well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe in the truthe of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, for to communicate withe them / for I ſpeake not, but by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (to whom god hath opened his truth) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> how great filthines the whole papiſticall church is repleniſhed. To iudg now well of this matter, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary to be noted that of that which men call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruyce of god there is one parte whiche was Inſtitute all together directly againſt god: another part hath bene depraued and abuſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faulte of them whiche miſuſed it. Albeit that at the beginning the firſt origenall was not euil. Further that there be many ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies whiche a man by no meanes can excuſe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:25772:28"/>
conteyne playn ydolatry. Now there be other which be vayne and folyſſhe, neuertheles of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues they cannot defile a man excepte that a man in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge of them haue any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious opinion. Thirdely we muſt marke that there be ſome thinges that were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded wickedly whiche notwithſtan- a chriſtian man may kepe with out offence. Other ther be whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che may not, neyther ought not in any wyſe to be obſerued. It is not neceſſary for to handle or entreat of all theſe kyndes one after another ſeuerally. It is ſufficient to touche them to the intent that a man may know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am not ſo ſharpe &amp; extreame as altogether and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to forbid a chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:28"/>
that he may not confirme hym ſelfe to the Papiſtes in any ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rymonye of obſeruation: for I intende not to condempne any other thinge then that whiche is playne euyll and manifeſtely naught. And bycauſe this can not be well vnderſtande but by examples, without goinge any further about the buſſhe, let vs ſet forthe the thinge euen as it is, amongeſt the papiſtes there is maſſe ſonge dayly, they that wyl ſeme more deuoute then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, go to the churche to heare it: whether may thys thynge now be excuſed? Who ſoeuer hath but meanely profited in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell is not ignorante but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing is none other than playn ſacrilege &amp; abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the prieſtes do there. I praye
<pb facs="tcp:25772:29"/>
you, may a man go to bow hym ſelfe before an Idoll, that eueri man ſhould know that he hath a deuotion to a wicked thynge and it not ſyn in ſo doing? But if it be ſo, what ſhoulde become of that that the holy ghoſte ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of ſainct Paul that we haue not to do with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfrutefull workes of darknes but rather ſhould reproue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> Beholde a worke that I know to be wicked and doth diſpleaſe god / I haue to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it. I make as though I accepte it &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinke that I haue clene handes. What is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> anye other thinge then (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyd ſpeaketh) for to ſay wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked let vs do hardely that that liketh vs / for god ſeeth vs not?<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note> But theſe men do allege.
<pb facs="tcp:25772:29"/>
It is not we that do it, but ſyn. What can we do ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it lyeth not in our power to amend it? I anſwere that the euyll which I reproue is in them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> abſteine not from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thinge whiche they know to be euyll: but defile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues by wrappyng them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in it. And in dede touching this poincte it is not harde to ſtoppe their mouthes. Now of hye maſſe it ſemeth to many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath a better cloke &amp; a more apparant ſhyne, for all thoughe (ſay they) that there be moche corruption in it (which we can approue) neuertheleſſe, for as moch as to vs it is as it were a memorial of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do we take it) then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we come there it is to reduce into our memory the death &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25772:30"/>
paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lord Ieſus, well is the matter at that poynt that we may tranſforme thinges af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter our appetit &amp; ſay that dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is light. I pray you what ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>militude is betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament inſtitute of the lorde Ieſus and this confection co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of euyll. Firſt to ſpeke of that that the maſſe is holden for a ſacrifice, by whiche god is pacified not only w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lyuing, but alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dead, think they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is nothinge? Is this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nother, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is as it were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principall ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe, is full of ſuch abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable blaſphemies? In lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers for the ſoules in purgatorie which we knowe to be altogyther ſuperſticious?</p>
            <p>But yf there were no more but
<pb facs="tcp:25772:30"/>
this deueliſh Imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to ſacrifice Ieſus Chriſt vnto god to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a worke ſhuld be a ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; an atto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quicke &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, is not this a manifeſt denieng of his death &amp; paſſion: the which is made of no value if that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge it for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only &amp; perpetuall ſacrifice? Is it not a playne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the holy ſupper? It is ſure that theſe two ſo abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable pollutions ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no more be ſeperated from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, then heat from fyer. Whoſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thervnto to be partaker of it / can he be puer and cleane commyttyng ſuche an acte? Is this the honor which we beare vnto God our father and to Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our maiſter &amp; redea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, that when we ſee ſuche a
<pb facs="tcp:25772:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſpytefull dede done of one and other, in the ſteade of ſpeakyng againſt it, do come &amp; ioyne our ſelues vnto hym that dothe it? And that worſe is, do allure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our examples to do as muche. Is it not to ſhamefull to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man in diſhonouring of god and gyuing example vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his neyghbour doth none e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll at all? Then is their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry which paſſeth all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, to worſhippe a pyece oft breade as God, and to ſay that it is no more bread but god him ſelfe. If that ſame were the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of our lorde whiche there were duly myniſtred, we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t well than, that there ſhoulde be a true ſpirituall receyuinge of the bodye and bloude of Ieſus Chriſte. But yet therfore were
<pb facs="tcp:25772:31"/>
not this as moch as to ſay that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of bread were chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body were hidden within it. For the ſupper is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to cauſe vs to lyfte vp our myndes on heyght vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not for to fyxe them vpon theſe viſible thinges and ſygnes of bread and wine, which be there preſent with vs.</p>
            <p>Now then / if this were the very ſupper in dede, it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perilous &amp; a dampnable fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye, to worſhyp a piece of bread in the ſteade of Ieſus Chriſte. Other elſe to ſeke hym there. But it is not now neceſſarye to enter into his diſputation. For by what meanes belongeth it vnto the maſſe this promes of Ieſus Chriſte, when in geuing of the bread he ſayde take, eate,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:32"/>
this is my bodye, whiche ſhall be deliuered for you. For before he promiſeth any thinge, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth that the ſacramente be diſtributed amonge the faith full. Is this done at the maſſe? No but rather contrary wyſe, the prieſte doth his buſynes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone aparte as though he wold exclude and excommunicate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole congregation.</p>
            <p>Thinke we then that in doyng altogither contrary to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt ordeyned, we haue him yet tied to our gyrdles for to play with hym as with a lytle babye? Or elſe rather as a tenys Ball for to whirle him here and there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyn as it pleaſeth vs? Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, he addeth, that we do ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate his ſacrament in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of him there by preching
<pb facs="tcp:25772:32"/>
hys death with prayſe and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of thankes. Now, howe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this be done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, wher there is not ſo moche as one worde vnderſtand: but altogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is done and ſpoken in an vnknowen tongue. Moreouer it is vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iheſus Chriſte directeth him ſelf in promiſing vs in the communion of his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, when he geueth vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall bread. In the maſſe is there nothinge of all this, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prieſt after the faſſhion of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters or Iugglers bloweth vpon the bread to charme and cuniure it. Wherfore, thinke ye this to be good? To be ſhorte, ye ſhall as ſone proue, that ther is any ſimilytude betwene the Popes maſſe and the ſupper of our lorde as that the day ſhold
<pb facs="tcp:25772:33"/>
no more be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyghte Then what elles can the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping be which men do ther to the breade, than abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Idolatry. yea more groſſe &amp; more folyſſhe then euer was any amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Painyms. Now let vs ſe with how good a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience a chriſtian man may be preſent there, for to faſhion him ſelf there lyke vnto other men. Beholde an Idoll that is lyfte vp on hygh on the ſhoulders to be called vpon and worſhipped as God. I ſhall fall downe on my knees I ſhall make proteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to worſip it. And then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde I wold not that any man ſhoulde reproue me what meaneth all this? Though no man ſhould ſpeake a word doth not the acte it ſelfe accuſe me y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb facs="tcp:25772:33"/>
wherefore though men do ſpare me, yet god wyll not ſpare me. Now yf there were no more but this, I ſe not what cloke any faythfull ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can fynd for to purge hym ſelfe, that he ſhoulde not be faultye in thus doynge. And yet neuertheleſſe perceyuinge that they haue no thynge to laye for them, do not yet ceaſe to fynd cauyllations pretendynge the auctoritie of this man, or that man, for their buckeler. But to what purpoſe muſt we ſet thopinyon of men plat agaynſt the worde of god? I apeale theyr owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, yf the ſame do not condempne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what ſhall it then helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be abſolued of men when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god they be conuynced for to do euyll. But this is it that
<pb facs="tcp:25772:34"/>
I ſaide at the begynninge that, manye do aſke me, not for to know the verite but to haue an anſwere agreable to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre. And our lorde to punyſſhe their hipocriſye, ſuffereth them to fynde ſuche as they ſeke: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is none other but vnto their more greuous confuſion.</p>
            <p>But for as moche as this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll is wont to ſprede it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode very farre euen almoſte among all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for to haue more cleare and eaſy declaration of this matter: let vs conſyder in a ſome, that whiche men be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye accuſtomed to do. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then, what euery man will do for his owne parte, I ſpeake ſpecially of the better ſorte of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worldely wyſe people, whyche wyll enterteyne and kepe them
<pb facs="tcp:25772:34"/>
ſelues in the fauour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: on the ſundaye he wyll not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly take holy water (as they call it) with other lyke cerymonies and alſo go to the Maſſe, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo vpon all other holy dayes, of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which one part was inſtitute, of very manyfeſte ſuperſtition: there one ſyngethe Maſſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honoure of a Saincte, yea, oft ſuch one where of there is none other probation, then that the Pope hath put hym in hys pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice. But yet although it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re a Sainct approued, ſhal one ſynge Maſſe in the honoure of hym? Can there be any gretter abhomynation, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tranſfer the Sacramente of our lorde vnto ſuch an abuſe? And thinke we that the lord will make him ſelfe ſubiecte vnto ſuche fylthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?
<pb facs="tcp:25772:35"/>
Beſides this, what pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers do they make there? Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ones and ſtuffed withe blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemyes. Let hym that dothe communicate withe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, excuſe hym ſelfe yf he can. Now euery man doth this commonly. If y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I or any other wolde flatterre them in this, were it not euen to betraye the truthe?</p>
            <p>Now when any man ſhall be maryed, where as he ought to repreſente hym ſelfe before god and hys churche, that his mary age myghte be bleſſed. Fyrſte there ſhalbe many folyſſhe gan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, whiche be mete do defyle him. Finally, he ſhal pollute him ſelfe altogether by byinge of a Maſſe with his owne monye. I demaunde this of you? when the Prieſt ſelleth the Maſſe, is
<pb facs="tcp:25772:35"/>
it not ſacriledge? What ſhall we ſay then of hym that byethe it? Our lord ſayth, that a good make is a ſpeciall gyfte of hys goodnes, now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it were mete for hym to geue hym thankes &amp; to deſyre hym to accompliſhe that which he hath begonne in makynge the maryage to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Is not this to prouoke his wrathe, for to vſe ſuch abhomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? We knowe all how moch our lord doth honour mariage, and in what eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wolde that we ſhoulde haue the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therof, when he compareth it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirituall vnion, which he hath w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his people thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of his holy ſpirite. Shal we polute y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ieſus, &amp; begyn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame with the denying of his death?
<pb facs="tcp:25772:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Do not we thinke that the lord wyll punyſſhe greuouſely ſuch outragiouſenes? The mariage fyniſſhed, they haue a chylde: where as he ſhoulde be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the lord for to receiue baptyſme puerly after his inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: in the ſtead of the ſame he is defyled withe very manye peruerſe and prophane cerymo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies. It is truthe that becauſe of the ſame, the baptyſme cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to haue hys vertue as touchynge the chylde, bycauſe the holy ordinaunce of god can not be abholiſhed by the folyſhe inuentions of men: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father ſhall not be excuſed of ſynne in conſentynge to ſuche a mynyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of baptiſme, which is al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>together faulty and corrupte. I paſſe ouer the Iewes ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition
<pb facs="tcp:25772:36"/>
which is vſed at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng of the mother and at her commynge abrode. Nowe we wyll come vnto inſtruction off a howſholde. Who is he that hath any care to haue hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes ryghtly taught for to ſerue god after hys worde? Is it not rather a thyng to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, to let them lyue in ignoraunce lyke brute beſtes, and wythout carefulneſſe of withdrawynge them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idolatry? But there is great daunger (ſay they) to ſpeake vnto them. Let vs paſſe ouer to ſpeake of the daunger for this preſente tyme. Shal y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be a lette that men ſhoulde not do it? Is it reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde be ſerued euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his houſe and that god be there not with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng diſhonoured? Thynke
<pb facs="tcp:25772:37"/>
we that a houſholde deſerueth to proſper in whiche god is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoueraigne lorde? And what do I ſpeake of ſeruantes, howe many fathers are there which dare inſtruct (as they ought to do) their wyues and children? yet neuertheles, for as moche as theſe faultes do rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare one to be neglygent in do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge hys dutie, then to offende god in doinge expreſly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: I do not proſecute in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thynge agaynſte them ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry bitterly. For as moch as my intent is, to ſpeake of ſuche dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des as men commyt agaynſte the commaundement of god: &amp; be tranſgreſſynges of his law.</p>
            <p>All we which haue receyued the pure doctryne of the goſpel do graunt well that their diry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:25772:37"/>
and obſequies for the dead be very abhomynable. Fyrſte, for as moche as, they were at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynninge inuented falſely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the ſcripture, and alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be derogacion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death and Paſſion of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now yf that a mans father or frend do dye or a neighbour he that calleth him ſelf a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an man will go with the other, makinge as though he prayed for hys ſoule. What cloke haue they for this, except it be ſuche a one as can not kepe away the rayne? Nowe, yf the father or wyfe dye, he will not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue theſe ſacrileges in ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge by them: but wil alſo bye them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mony: yf the prieſt in ſellinge the Maſſe do folowe
<pb facs="tcp:25772:38"/>
the market of Iudas.</p>
            <p>Now he that putteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in practyce and geueth him wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, ſhall he be gyltleſſe? I will ſpeake nothing of that men do all the reſt of the yere: I wil on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly entreat of the feaſt of Eaſter What do al they then commun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, which do profeſſe the Goſpel They ſticke not to go vnto con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion, not onely to ſatiſfye the tyrannous commandement of Antychriſte: but alſo conſent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemyes that ſhall pleaſe the Prieſte to pronounce ouer them, and by ſuche conſentinge as it were ſealed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for as the Prieſt doth gyue abſoluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the auctorite of the ſeate Apoſtolyke (that is to ſaye) of the Idole of Rome, whiche can do none other but deſtroye and
<pb facs="tcp:25772:38"/>
curſe, euen ſo muſt he receue it as a very holſom thing. I aſke whether this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be found good that a Chriſten man ſhuld pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him ſelfe and fawle downe before the vicare or depute of Antichriſt, for to receyue remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes, in the ſteade of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche he oughte to ſeke at the miniſter of the Goſpell. In like wyſe, he enioyneth him pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but what is it? It is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munly to mumble vp certayne Aue Maries, before a crucifix, to cauſe Maſſes to be done, or to do other lyke Idolatry, And to what purpoſe? Forſothe to make ſatiſfaction vnto God, &amp; to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence him. If this work may be allowed, I can not ſee, what ſynne one maye reproue in all the worlde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:39"/>But to thintent I be not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlonge, let euery man recken with him ſelfe the dampnable ſuperſtitions whiche they then commit in thre or fower dayes And who is he that abſteyneth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, it is poſſible that ther be ſome, but the numbre is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall. A Chriſten man wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hathe lyued continually in this fylth and myre, yet cometh there worſe at the deathe, for then is it, that the deuell trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth him and gyueth him moſt aſſautes, for ether friers or prie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes ſhalbe at his elbowe, for to ſeduce and deceyue him, vnto whom although he conſent not yet muſt he neuertheleſſe grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them ſomwhat, and make vnto them a good face. What torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhall he fynde in his hart, which
<pb facs="tcp:25772:39"/>
muſte immediately appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his iudge Ieſus Chriſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he hathe bene aſhamed or afraied to confeſſe him? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderinge that this ſentence is gyuen alredy,<note place="margin">Mark. 8.</note> that who ſo euer is aſſhamed of me or of my wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des before men, of him wil I be aſſhamed when I ſhall come in myne and my father glory w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Aungelles. I thoughte I wolde ſet out this myrrour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men in the whiche euerye faithfull man (that lyueth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges the papiſtes) might behold the faultes, which he doth, and the curſed eſtate wherin he is.</p>
            <p>Now haue I brieffely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended them in a groſſe ſom louinge rather to dyminiſh and leaue many thinges oute, then to amplifie and enlarge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
<pb facs="tcp:25772:40"/>
which of it ſelf is but to bad.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo, whan a man truly fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe God and comparinge of that he doth, with that whiche is here writen, ſhall knowledge that he ſynneth double ſo moch in other thinges which I haue not ſpoken of. And then he ſhal haue good occaſion to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him ſelf: and ſhall not dare to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his mouth to defende him.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there be ſome which thinke all good ynoughe when they haue ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me excuſe, as it were a buckler for to put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. A man muſt beat out of their handes all that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were wont to arme, and helpe them ſelues. It is a very commun thinge to alledg thexemple of Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chief Capitayne of the kynge of the <note place="margin">4. Reg. 5.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:40"/>
Aſſirians warres, who after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had made profeſſion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> from thence for the he wolde worſhip the god of Iſraell: neuertheles aſked leue of the prophet Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus for to entre with the kyng hys maſter into the tempe of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Idoll whiche was worſhypped in his contrey. And bicauſe the kyng leaned vpon his ſhoulder he demaunded, that whether when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge enclyned or bow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed downe hym ſelfe, yf it were not lefull for hym to ſtoupe or bowe. Now for as moche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete did graunt hym this, it ſeameth vnto dyuers that it were not euyll done for a man to fayne or dyſſemble in a lyke caſe. I wyl then direct my wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des agaynſte hym which wold pretende this colour for to iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify
<pb facs="tcp:25772:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hym ſelf and wyll anſwere hym. My frynde I meruell to moche, that ſeinge thou haſte the generall worde of God as a great hygh way alredy made and beat on, in the whiche thou canſte not fayle, how it cometh to paſſe, that thou haddeſte ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declyne vnto one partycu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple which is (as it were) a narowe pathe and lytle vſed in the which thou mayſt lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go out of the way. How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth it that thou art ſo ſuttle to ſeke out ſtertyng holes, and canſt not ſee at all whyche way to enter in at the gate? Doeſte thou not knowe well, that it is a thyng not very ſure, to folow the perticuler examples wyth out hauyng other approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For our lorde dyd ſome tyme
<pb facs="tcp:25772:41"/>
permyt vnto ſome of hys faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful (as it were by priuilege) that which he did forbid to all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. In lyke wyſe, he hathe ſuffered that thynge which he hathe not therfore approued. We reade not that Naaman, of whome we now ſpeake, was at any tyme cyrcumciſed: and it is not verye lyke that he was in dede. Wilt thou excuſe thy ſelfe therfore, that thou ſhuldeſt not receyue baptyſme? And wylte thou ſay, if I wyll now reaſon the contrary, that in as moche as the worſhyppynge and the confeſſynge of hys name proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of faythe: loke how moche more cleare knoweledge thou haſte then Naaman, ſo moche art thou more bounde to geue glory vnto god? I put caſe I an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb facs="tcp:25772:42"/>
the thus. It is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though he were by the prophete ſente agayne wyth ſuche permyſſion, ſeynge he had but a very lytle ſparke of the veryte: but thou whiche haſte a great meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhouldeſt thou ordre it ſo as though thou were not more bounde to confeſſe god the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he? God is no ſophiſter to receiue ſuche euaſions, ſhall thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then be in reſte? But yet I haue an other anſweare for ſuche maner of people: for I do ſay, that they do falſely abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture in this place, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al is well conſydered. Fyrſt we muſt conſyder that the kynges chief capytayne in his ydolatry was wonte to do many ſacryfices, ſeyng that euery perticular per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:25772:42"/>
of meane eſtate dyd ſo. And what doth Naaman promyſe among other tynges? He pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſteth that he wyll neuer do ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice more but onely vnto the God of Iſrael. Nowe is it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne, that thys was as moche as to make profeſſion openly &amp; knowne vnto all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, that he is no more an Idolater: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he had cauſed it to be proclai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med by the ſound of a trompet. For who is he that can doubte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had not forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ceaſſed to make all thoſe ſacrifyces, whyche he was wonte to do afore tyme? Furthermore, he requireth to cary away of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth of Iſrael as moch as two Moiles might carye, that he myght ſacryfyce there vnto the lyuynge god: to
<pb facs="tcp:25772:43"/>
thentente he myght not defyle hym ſelfe by ſacrifycynge vpon an heathen grownde. Haue ye not here now a nother ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne declaracion whiche he maketh to put away all doubte, that he wolde not lyue any longer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperſtition of the Aſſyryans? yea but afterwarde he aſked leaue for to woſhip in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of Remmon. If that were to make as though he worſhipped the Idoll, it ſhoulde haue ſome apperaunce for them, but nowe a man may ſe the contrary. Be holde the wordes whiche he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, yf the kynge my maſter do peraduenture entre in to the temple of Remmon, and that he do worſhyppe there leanynge vpon my hande: yf I worſhyp alſo lykewyſe, that the lorde im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pute
<pb facs="tcp:25772:43"/>
not the ſame vnto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt. This worde worſhyppe is as moch to ſay, as to enclyne or bow downe. Wherfore is it then that he ſayth expreſly, yf the kyng leanyng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my hand do worſhyppe? Forſothe to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfie that he wolde not bowe downe, but for good maners ſake, that he myghte be no let vnto the kynge. Then in that he enclyned or bowed downe his body it was not for to make as though he worſhypped the ydol, but for to rendre and giue hys accuſtomed dutye to the kynge. Let hym then that wyl defende hym ſelfe wyth thexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Naaman, fyrſte pourge hym ſelf of all ſuperſtition and ydolatry, and declare that he wyll in no wyſe conſent vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
<pb facs="tcp:25772:44"/>
Nowe when he hath made thys knowen, we ſhall be no len<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger in controuerſy. But I pray you, what a mockynge is thys, to allege thexample of Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to couer or cloke them wythe: when there is ſo greate a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the matter? For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do, is nothinge els but to ſhew that they will playe the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with other Idolatres. A man can not ſatiſfye God with ſuche vayne and tryflinge cauil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lations.</p>
            <p>I haue hearde ſome alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that that is on this wyſe written in the Epiſtle that is aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cribed vnto Ieremye,<note place="margin">Baruc. 6.</note> when ye ſhall ſee the Babilonians beare aboute their goddes of golde &amp; ſiluer and that all men doo fall downe before them, ye ſhall ſay
<pb facs="tcp:25772:44"/>
in your hartes, it is thou lorde whiche oughteſt to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. But doth thauctor of this epiſtle in exhortyng the people of Iſrael, to geue glorye vnto god in their hartes, ſuffer them to make curteſy vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ydoles? What helpeth them ſo folyſhly to abuſe that ſame ſentence?</p>
            <p>And I praye you, he that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly doth honour vnto Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, how can he ſaye in his hert that vnto God he ought to doo it: except he do accuſe his owne dede and condempne him ſelfe before the iudgement of God? As for me, I require not of the faithfull, that when thei ſee the Papiſtes beare about their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques and other mamettes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde ſnatche them oute of their handes or els caſt dirte
<pb facs="tcp:25772:45"/>
at theym, for it belongeth vnto Princes and hygher powers to correct ſuche abhominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but that they do abſteyne from fylinge them ſelues with them And ſeynge they maye not be ſuffred to worſhyp God openly that they do yet at the leaſt glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rifye God in their hartes and abſteyn from outwarde Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try. Thexemple of S. Paule lykewyſe, whiche they alledge, hath a lytle more apparance w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it, but it ſerueth them moche leſſe then that ſame of Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we haue proued to ſerue them nothinge at all.<note place="margin">Act. 21.</note> S. Paul (ſaye they) knowinge wel, that the ceremonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe were abolyſſhed, yet for to pleaſe his nacion dyd vſe them in ſhauing and purifyeng of him ſelf, after
<pb facs="tcp:25772:45"/>
the cuſtome of the lawe, for to offer in the temple. Now it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that, if S. Paul ſynned not in doyng thus: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is no more euyll done to go vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Maſſe for a face, and to do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges whiche I do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. I anſwere, that they do great iniurye: fyrſte vnto god, for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare a ceremony which he hath inſtitute with an ydola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try all together wicked and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynable: as is the papiſticall Maſſe. Secondarely, vnto S. Paul, to laye to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath done ſuch an acte, as they them ſelues do: but loke what it is when men wyll cleare them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues in euyll doyng: a man doth allwayes defyle hym ſelfe dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. This Ceremony that S. Paul vſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was it reproued
<pb facs="tcp:25772:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of god of elſe was it indifferent yet durynge the tyme vntyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell was better and more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſprede abrode? There is no man which wyll not graunt me, that of it ſelfe it was none euyll thyng, neyther yet damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: for it was in veri dede of it ſelfe a ſacryfice of prayſe and giuynge of thankes that he did vnto god. The ſhauynge and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puryfyeng were in dede of the ſhadowes of the law: but there was yet no inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that a chriſtian man myght vſe them vnto edifiynge. And this is it that Saincte Paul hym ſelfe ſayth,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> that he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Iewe vnto the Iewes, to the intente that he myghte wynne them: and dyd obſerue the law bycauſe he might draw
<pb facs="tcp:25772:46"/>
them to the goſpell. In thys Maſſe what thynge is there like vnto thys? I take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe for all other maner of faſſhions of doynge, wherin there is any euydent Idolatry or elſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtition altogether fyghtyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the worde of god. What reaſon is it then to applye the dede of Saincte Paul, whiche was none other but good, for to maynteyne thynges that be all together naught? yf it be al one a man to ſhame hym ſelfe and to fall downe before an Idoll: then wolde I graunte them to folow the example of Saincte Paul: but to put thinges toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a rome that be nothyng lyke, it is to confounde all toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. How be it, ther is yet more to be regarded, that is thente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:25772:47"/>
and ende of the thyng: for if S. Paul to kepe him ſelf in fauour of the worlde, and for the feare of hys fleſſhe, dyd vſe ſuch diſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mulation, he ſhoulde be the firſt that wolde reproue hym ſelfe. But we know that he had none other conſideration, then for to edifie the poore ignorante and rude people, and that he myght offende no perſon. Who be they now a dayes whych dare boaſt them ſelues of ſuch a zeale, for their owne conſcience doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preue them? yet neuertheleſſe, muſte we contende aboute this matter, as though there were ſome doubte in it, for ye ſhal ſee a great nombre of them, which do counterfaicte for to enter in them ſelues wyth the papiſtes, and do coloure and cloke them
<pb facs="tcp:25772:47"/>
ſelues wyth this goodly cloke. We do it not but bycauſe we wolde not offende. Fyrſte I do ſende ſuche kynde of perſonnes vnto the iudgement of god &amp; to the wytneſſe of theyr owne conſciences, where ye ſhall fynd that they haue none other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, but to auoyde trouble &amp; daunger. What wyn we nowe I prai you, to flatter our ſelues eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verite? &amp;c. What ſhall it helpe vs to defende our ſelues by lyes, when I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented an excuſe? Beholde my honor is decked that I am not addicte neyther to my bely nor yet vnto ambition: and yet not wythſtandynge I know well &amp; can not deny that there is none other thynge that dryueth me vnto it. But now ſome man wil
<pb facs="tcp:25772:48"/>
lay to my charge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I do raſſhly to iudge the ſecrete thoughtes and that the ſame belongethe onely vnto God. I anſwer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my iudgemente is proued true inough, by that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeth wythe hys eyes. Let vs not mocke with god. If there were no feare of loſynge of the lyfe or of the goodes or auctoryte or acquayntaunce or the fauoure of frendes, whiche do hynder a man, frely to do or ſpeake: ſhold a man fynd amonge a hundred yea one amonge a thouſande which wolde diſſemble ſo as all men do nowe? But ſeynge the worlde is come vnto ſuche an vnſhamefaſtneſſe for to mocke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſo, I graunte that their intent be ſuche as they pretend and I wyll no further inuey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:25772:48"/>
theyr hipocriſy. Let vs now examyne the dede it ſelfe, for feare to offend (ſay they) we be conſtrayned to make a good countenance in faſſhionyng our ſelues vnto the ſuperſtitions of the papiſtes.</p>
            <p>Now to ſee whether it be ſo or no, we muſt fyrſt vnderſtand what it is to offende, for when S. Paul vſeth thys worde, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, he ſignifieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troublyng of a conſcience wherby it is let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to come vnto Ieſus Chriſt or cauſe to fall or drawe backe from hym, now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thys matter of whiche we ſpeake of, he commaundeth vs to be well ware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we offend no man, well how is that? Take hede (ſayth he) that thou eateſt not of the Offerynges made
<pb facs="tcp:25772:49"/>
vnto Idolles in the preſence of a weake perſon that is ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,<note place="margin">1 Corin. 8</note> for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is an offence. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? For ſothe in as moche as hys conſcience is therby edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do euyll, for he thynketh that ſuch meate is defyled, and yet neuertheleſſe, he ſtyckethe not to eate of it, folowing thine example. Beholde nowe how thou art cauſe of hys ruyne, or elſe, if he abſteyn, he is troubled in his harte, thynkynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou diſpleaſyſte god in ſo doynge: and is by this meanes ſet as it were on fier, and in daunger to giue ouer, bicauſe he is not wel grounded in the truthe of god. We ſee then from what offence Saincte Paul calleth vs backe it is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we through our raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be the cauſe that a weake
<pb facs="tcp:25772:49"/>
parſon doth ſo ſtumble, that he fall vnto ruyne, or turne from the ryght way, or elſe be hynde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, and to be ſhorte. When we plucke hym backe, or be a let vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym to profyte in oure lorde in the ſteade of that we ought for to further hym. In lyke maner, to the Romayns.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> After that he had ſhewed, that it was an vnfryndly thyng &amp; agaynſte charite, for to trouble a weake perſon bycauſe he maketh hys conſcience to eate of all maner of meates and that he ſhoulde not conſtrayn hym: not to be to importune agaynſt hys conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Fynally, that he ſhold not dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort nor dyſcourage hym. And when he wolde conclude hys purpoſe he ſayth. Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſe hys neighbour in
<pb facs="tcp:25772:50"/>
well doynge vnto hys edyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge.</p>
            <p>Now, we ſee the marke wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnto we muſt haue an eye, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we go aboute to auoide offence, it is that we gyue not an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vnto our neyghboure to be edyfyed in euyll, nor yet gyue hym any euyll example, neither to ſay or do any thynge, where by he myght euer the ſoner, go out of the ryght waye. Where vpon, it is eaſy for vs to iudge, whether that they whych bow them ſelues vnto Idolles, and by their diſſemblynge of theyr chriſtianyte diſhonour god, do, by thys meanes auoyde offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge? Fyrſte, they ſhew them ſelues that they haue no great zeale vnto the glory of god, the whiche they do diſhonoure ſo.
<pb facs="tcp:25772:50"/>
Then do they entyce other to doe the ſame. I ſpeake of the feble and ſymple oons, whyche haue already ſome taſte of the truth. And where as otherwiſe they wolde make conſcience to defile them ſelues with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, they do take courage and boldnes, through their exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. Fynally, they confyrme the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuers and harden them in their errours. If this be not to offende, I confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am oute of my wytte. It is very trewe in dede, that they do not offend the worldly people or do runne into their diſpleaſure: neither do they prouoke any perſon for to perſecute them, nor giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any occaſion for to murmur or crye out againſte them. But in noryſſhyng of all Idolatry tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:25772:51"/>
their faynyng, they be the cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> breaketh his necke, other be greuouſly hurte, ſome do fall &amp; ſome be cauſed to halt, or elſe to wander out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way. And by this meanes they altogyther, euen from the fyrſt vnto the laſt be blynde and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blynd, for in folowing one an other lyke Cranes, they doo ſeduce or leade an other oute of the ryghte way. For as moche as neuer a one of them doth folow the worde of God whyche is the onely true rule. Moreouer we muſte note, that when S. Paule byddeth vs to condiſcende vnto the rudenes or infirmite of our neighbours that we gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none offence, he wolde not that we ſhould do any euyll thyng, for to do them
<pb facs="tcp:25772:51"/>
pleaſure with al: or elſe vſe any diſſimulacion, that is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs: but that in all indyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferente thynges whyche God hath lefte in our lybertye, and whiche of them ſelues be but good, we ſhoulde, haue reſpecte vnto them, and not to trouble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore the fyrſt founda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion ſhulde be euer to conſydre whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge where of we entreate, be letfe vs free, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we myghte vſe it in one ſorte or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puerly with out offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng god, that is to ſay, to do a dede or leue it vndone, to vſe a thing or to abſteyn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Now to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ydolatry in this row, it is to no purpoſe. Therfore in as moch as to counterfaict in ſuch ſort that one ſhuld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit all ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynation, is agaynſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb facs="tcp:25772:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
prohibition of god, there is no reaſon at all, to brynge forthe offence, to be an excuſe in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>Now, they that ſee me to be more indyfferente perceyuyng them ſelues to be voyde of all lawfull excuſes, do not wholely defende that thys is well done or that it is no ſynne to commit Idolatry, for the feare of men: but do alledge that it is a ſmall faulte and eaſy to be pardoned, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hert is not there wyth and therfore that it is to paſſe all meaſure, for to reproue it ſo bytterly. And for to gyue ſome ſhewe vnto theyr ſayeng, they doo obiect, that there be many vices remaynyng in the world moch more greuous then that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ought to be reproued
<pb facs="tcp:25772:52"/>
fyrſte of all. And therfore men ought not to begynne at thys ſmal infirmyte (as they do take it) yf we wyll not folow the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy of the Pharyſes which ſwalowed vp an whole Camel and ſtrayned the lyttle pieces there of throughe a ſeife.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> I will begyn to Anſwere at thys laſt poyncte, grauntyng that there be now a dayes very horryble faultes in the worlde, agaynſte whiche there is moche nede to crye. I confeſſe alſo that when one paſſeth ouer them lyghtly to tary vpon this onely ſynne of outwarde Idolatry, that he goeth not well to worke: euen as now I ſhould ſpare whores, dronkerdes, theues, diſceyuers periured perſonnes, and that I ſhould wynke at couetuouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:53"/>
that I diſſembled wyth extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioners, &amp; fynally, the pompes and pryde, or this world, beyng only &amp; altogither ſet to reproue this vice wherof I ſpeke now. For then I ſhoulde not do well, and alſo a man myght, by good ryghte reproue me of lacke of diſcreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as one that lefte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſecrete wondes alone for to be occupied aboute the healyng of one. But for as moche, as I do not ſee who ſhall let me to reproue euery vyce in hys or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, without leauynge any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched, nowe that this is one of the nombre, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be deny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. yea (ſay they) but yet it is to bytterly: for ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearyng you to crye ſo moche agaynſt it do thynke that they haue done all their dutye towardes God,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:53"/>
when they haue not fayned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be ydolatres, as other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do. And euen as all their ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes lay in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, they paſſe not to leade an inordinat life, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle their neighbours, or to do ſuch lyke thynges: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, I anſwer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch peple put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting al their perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in abſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an outwarde thynge &amp; goyng aboute to pleaſe god by doyng one only poyncte of his law, be euen as farre out of the way as thother which thynk y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they offende not God by forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of him through the vſyng of outward ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s before men. But it is no reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr faulte ſhoulde be imputed vnto me: conſiderynge I gyue them none occaſion. My doctrine is, that a faythfull man ought to
<pb facs="tcp:25772:54"/>
ſainctify &amp; conſecrate vnto god as wel the body, as the ſpiryte: but yet that the ſpiryte as the moſt pryncipall, haue the firſte place. Who is it nowe that can conclude vpon thys, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wolde brynge in any hypocryſie for to paye god wyth outwarde geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures onely? Touchynge that they do pretende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a ſmall fault, a man to feyne for to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Idolles, and therfore that it may lyghtly be forgeuen. To that I anſwere, that yf a man come to make comparyſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundementes of god fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thone to thother, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may well fynde thone greatter and thother ſmaller: euen as Ieſus Chriſt ſayde,<note place="margin">Math. 23</note> that the pryncipal poinctes of the lawe, be iuſtyce, iudgemente, &amp; fayth. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:54"/>
we conſider euery one of them ſeuerally, there is none of them which ought not to be of great eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, for we know thys,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> that Ieſus Chriſte oure maiſter ſayth. Who ſo euer ſhal breake one of the leſte of theſe commaundementes and ſhall teache men ſo to do, he ſhall be of no eſtymation in the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. What is it to teach me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to do? It is to make them beleue, that it is not very euil done for to tranſgres ſome commaundement of God: as though it were of ſmall valure, and by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> menes to gyue them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brydle to do euyll, and to dymy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhe the ſyn. Now, if he which makethe the breakynge of the commaundemente of god (how lytle ſo euer it ſemeth to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:25772:55"/>
our vnderſtandynge) more lyght than it is, be ſo condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: what ſhall become of them whyche ſay, that a man, whan he dothe playne agaynſte it in dede, may diſſemble hys faulte all togyther &amp; not be a knowen of it at all. And in dede, yf we had not a very peruerſe &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte iudgemente, we ſhoulde not dare open our mouthes, for to ſay, that it were a ſmal thing to do clene contrary to the wyl of god. For in as moche, as our lorde hath vouchſauyd to open to ſpeake of any thyng, what ſo euer it be, were not thys good reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery creature ſhould be moued at it for to gyue eare there vnto in feare: &amp; dylygent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to obſerue the ſame, that he ſpeaketh? Belongethe it vnto
<pb facs="tcp:25772:55"/>
vs to enquyre, wherfore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth or forbyddeth anye thynge? As thoug hys onely wyll were not ſufficiente vnto vs for a reaſon.</p>
            <p>Now, to thentente that we dyſceyue not oure ſelues, we ought not onely, to loke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng commaunded or forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: but vnto god whiche ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can not diſobeye hys worde wythoute dyſpyſynge of hys maieſtye. Therfore it is after hys hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought to eſteme thof<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence, &amp; in ſo doing, it ſhal neuer ſeme ſmal to vs. For this cauſe, he ſayth by hys prophete zacha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry.<note place="margin">zacha. 5.</note> That he wold ſende a boke of curſe, by whych euery periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red perſon &amp; euery thief ſhould be accurſed togyther. Wherby,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:56"/>
he ſignyfyeth, that no man can tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſe his law, in what ſort ſo euer it be: but that it is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnable.<note place="margin">Iaco. 2.</note> Which thyng Saincte Iames doth expound yet more clearely, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith. He that hath kepte the whole law and offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in one poynct, ſhall be counted gyltie of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther. For he that hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den to murder, hath alſo forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den to play the whoremonger, to robbe, or to lye.</p>
            <p>Now, to ſhew, what offence it is to fayle in any poyncte, he ſendeth vs vnto God whiche gaue the lawe, as thoughe he wold ſay, that the faulte ought to be meaſured and wayed by this that we do agaynſt the wil of god, euen by contempte, as it were, ſettyng nothynge by hys
<pb facs="tcp:25772:56"/>
ſeueritie, as moche as is in vs. Wherfore our lord Ieſus Criſt reprouynge the hypocriſy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scrybes and phariſees:<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> which in ſuch wyſe did apply their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye to obſerue the ſmalleſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes, that the pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypall were lefte behynde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, ſayde not vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That they ſhoulde go aboute to do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche he had moſte chiefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and paſſe ouer the reſte: but contrarywyſe, he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth euen thus. Theſe thynges ought you to do &amp; not to leaue thother vndone: as though he wolde ſay, there is neuer a one of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes which one ought to dyſpyſe from the greateſt vnto the leaſt: nor one ſhoulde not vtterly reiecte the one, for to kepe the other. We
<pb facs="tcp:25772:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſee then, that it is a perilous fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy to conceiue, that it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall ſynne and lyghtlye to be pardoned, for to tranſgres any commaundement of god, what ſo euer it be: conſiderynge that, loke what feare and reuerence we beare vnto his maieſty: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ſhoulde we ſhewe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde all the poynctes of his lawe, euen from the hygheſt, to the loweſt. And in dede, when we ones begynne to extenuate or dymynyſſhe the word of god in any poyncte, for to bryng vs here vnto, that we paſſe not to do that which is commaunded, it is an entraunce for vs, for to cauſe vs afterwarde for to caſt it of altogether.</p>
            <p>Thus, euery thyng that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth agaynſt the wyll of god in
<pb facs="tcp:25772:57"/>
one ſorte or other, indifferently ought to be rebuked and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly reproued. For in this do we ſhew our ſelues to fere hym and that we wyl be ſubiecte vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym, yf that we do not omyt one onely tytle of all that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth. How be it, I wolde fayne knowe what reaſon it is, to call outwarde Idolatry one of the ſmalleſte offences that a man may do. Some man wyll ſay vnto me, it is bicauſe I haue not the wyll or thentente to do it, but do it by conſtraynt, deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge to doo otherwyſe, yf I myght be ſuffered. I wyll axe of hym then that ſayth ſo. My frende, yf that thou for feare of dyſpleſure, or for drede of ſome daunger, doſt a greate outrage or vylanye to thy father, ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſte
<pb facs="tcp:25772:58"/>
thou therfore be holden excuſed? And howe moche leſſe oughteſt thou to diſhonor God by prophanyng or vnhalowing hys holy name, by gyuyng glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vnto a Mammet. Thou art conſtrayned (thou ſayeſt) thinkeſt thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he eſtemeth not moche more hys glory, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy life &amp;c. But for to put away all contentions altercations, I deſyre all them whyche be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in ſuche erroure, that they wyll bethynke them a lytle, if it be a lyght faulte to maynteyne that by which S. Paul ſaithe. That god is prouoked euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt one which wolde fyght agaynſt hym, by which he ſaith, that Ieſus Chriſte is offended that one forſaketh hys holy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> and that one is made parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker
<pb facs="tcp:25772:58"/>
of the dyuels table, here be wordes (as me thinketh) able ynoughe to make vs tremble: yea, and to ſaye the truthe, they beate downe all outwarde Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry more mightely than I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſe. But ſome man will re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply againſt me, &amp; ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I abuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to wreſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Let vs ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether it be ſo or no. The chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people eyther for feare of daunger, or for other worldly reſpectes, did aſſemble in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, for to make ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne bankets in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour of Idolles: &amp; their excuſe was. In our hartes we condempne al their ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and know that there is but one onely God, vnto whome all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is due. Vpon this Sainct Paul ceaſyth not to crye, that
<pb facs="tcp:25772:59"/>
they prouoke the lord vnto bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayle, and pollute them ſelues with communycating with the Deuyls table. What is it that they do leſſe, whyche come to knele downe at the Maſſe, for to approue all thabomynation that is done there: and whyche is vſynge of all the paruerſe ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, &amp; ſuche as be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnto God, which men do in the kyngdome of Antychriſt, do ſhewe them ſelues to be obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyent chyldren, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye do fayne that they conſente vnto them and receyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as good? If they deny this, let vs ſe whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes for which Sainct Paul is ſo ſharpe agaynſte the Corynthians ſhal not be found in them. It is certeyn, that he conſydered twoo thynges, it is
<pb facs="tcp:25772:59"/>
that the Corynthyans by ſuche diſſemblyng, dyd gyue occaſion vnto the Infydeles, and Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyms to harden them in theyr euyl, and not to regard the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian relygion. And that on the other ſyde, the ſymple weake people were ſubuerted &amp; theyr conſciences troubled.</p>
            <p>Thus, bycauſe of the double offence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> folowed of their acte, he threteneth them ſo ſharply. And what do thei now a daies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be conformable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtes in their folyſſhneſſe? Let vs all wayes take the Maſſe for an example. They know well, that it is an abhomynatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet vp as it were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſpite of god, they knowe well for what purpoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people come togyther there, &amp; if there were none other thyng
<pb facs="tcp:25772:60"/>
there: they knowe that men do worſhyp there an Idol, lyftyng vp a piece of bread in the ſteade of God whyle they knowe this well ynough, do they not yet make as though they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped it as other men do? Wolde not they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſhoulde thynke that they do it of good deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In thys doyng (I pray them) do they not lay forth the glory of God to be mocked of the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked? Do not they offende the weake by gyuyng them an euil example with caſtynge them in doubte &amp; ſcrupuloſite that they wote not what to beleue? It is but loſte labour then for them to go aboute to make a lyghte matter of it, which we ſee to be ſo ſharpely reproued of God. And yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more is, it is a kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen
<pb facs="tcp:25772:60"/>
thynge, that the Maſſe is taken of the enymyes of Ieſus Chriſte as a gage for to bynde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lyue in their vngodlines: and to ſerue theyr tyranny. For yf any man go vnto the Maſſe deuoutly, he is taken for a good and a laudable ſupporter of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſte, contrariwyſe, to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe is as it ware to forſake the kyngdome off the Pope. Seyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is ſo, that a chriſtyan man in goynge to the Maſſe, doth gyue a teſtymonie and make a profeſſion that he wyll lyue in Idolatry, &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne thabomynations whiche raigne thys day in the worlde, is not the ſame a cloked forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of Ieſus Chriſte, and a playne denyeng of hys goſpell by crafte? What anſwere wyll
<pb facs="tcp:25772:61"/>
they make me vnto this, whych wolde coloure their ſynne and bycauſe they can not make it al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>togyther whyte, they wolde by ſome meanes darken it, that it ſhould not appeare at all. I ſay that we ought not to eſteme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe alonly in it ſelf: but with all the circumſtances and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inconueniences that folowe it. I ſaye further, that the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences be ſuche, that there a man maketh an obligation for to approue, retaine, and folowe the preſent eſtate of the popyſh churche, which all Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to abhorre and defye, yf they can aſſoyle me this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with a good conſcience &amp; without ſophiſtry, I diſcharge them, but that will not be this yere.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:61"/>I will yet recite vnto this purpoſe for the further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof, an Hiſtory that is in Ioſephus and in the boke of the Machabees,<note place="margin">2. Machu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6.7,</note> it is of Elea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zarus and a woman of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es with .vii. children that ſhe had, who al be it it were ſo, that men wolde conſtrayn them for to eate ſwynes fleſh, had yet ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther dye then to conſent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. It might ſeme at the firſt ſighte that this was rather a ſelfwilfulnes, to ſuffer deth for ſo ſmall a matter, then a righte ordered zeale. But yf we take hede wherevnto theſe tended, they might do none otherwyſe without forſakinge of God: for in conſtrayninge them to eate ſwynes fleſhe, whiche God had forbidden them, their purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:25772:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
was to haue a wytnes of them that they were content to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcende vnto the gentils ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lyuinge. This Hiſtory is not of the holy fcripture, but it is an act that was done in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede and no fable, yf we doo commende theſe perſonnes as martyres &amp; prayſe theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, doth it not become vs to condemne that that is done to the contrarye? Nowe to make an ende of this article, I ſaye, that all they, which take it for a ſmall fault, ſuch a fayning or diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſemblinge, to make as thoughe they agreed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolaters do not knowe in what eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on God hathe his honour, and haue neuer taſted of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which he ſpeaketh by his prophete Eſaye.<note place="margin">Eſai. 42.</note> I doo lyue, I
<pb facs="tcp:25772:62"/>
will not gyue my glorye to an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other: neyther yet my honour vnto Images, for by the ſame he ſheweth vs that he wyll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuffer, that hys honoure be gyuen vnto an Idole: but that he will at one tyme or at an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take vengeance of it, I ſay alſo, that they dyd neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the grace that God hath ſhewed vnto vs, in ordeyninge that our bodyes ſhoulde be the temples of his holy ſpirite, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had redemed them by the precious bloude of his ſonne our Lorde, and in promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge them glorye and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie in his kyngdome. For yf they vnderſtode this thynge, they wolde make this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with S. Paule, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were mete for vs to pourge vs from
<pb facs="tcp:25772:63"/>
all fylthynes as well of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as of the ſoule, and to beare God as well in thone, as in the other, conſyderynge that both of them be hys</p>
            <p>Now, after all theſe cauylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be beaten downe, my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy worldely wyſdome cometh in wyth her fyue egges, bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge in a perylouſe reaſon. What good ſhold come of it, yf euerye one wolde declare hym ſelfe for to ſerue God puerly? I anſwere wyth one woord, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf it pleaſed God, there myght folow of it moche perſecution, and that ſome myghte be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to flee, forſakynge all theyr goodes: eyther myghte be poyncted at with the fynger ſome put in pryſon, oother ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed, yea, and ſome myghte
<pb facs="tcp:25772:63"/>
loſe their lyues. I vnderſtand, euen as I haue ſayde yf that God wolde ſuffer it, but we ought to gyue this honour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to commit vnto him al that might come of it: truſting that he wolde ſo order the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, that he euyll (whiche we feared) ſhuld not come to paſſe for this is the refuge, wher vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our father Abraham bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs by hys example,<note place="margin">Gene. 22.</note> who hauynge commaundemente to kyll hys owne ſonne, when he was demaunded in the waye, what he wolde ſacryfice, ſayde. The lorde ſhall prouyde. It is trewly a ſentence, which ought to be writen in our hertes, that it myght come vnto our memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry by and by incontyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be amaſed in any thynge: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25772:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dryuen as it were vnto an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamyte, yf we coulde do ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wytte, to caſte all our care vpon God nothyng doubtyng but that he were wyſe ynough, for to directe vs vnto a good ende, when we be deſtitute of counſell and in perplexite, he wolde not fayle vs more then he dyd his ſeruaunt Abraham, in delyueringe him from all he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyneſſe, whan it was againſt al the helpe of man. But becauſe of our vnbelefe, we be not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to fele the goodnes of God towarde vs. When our Lorde commaundeth vs any thinge, thinke we, that he ſeeth not the daungers before hande, or els that he doeth not conſydere theym? And when he ſeeth them, thynke we, that he is
<pb facs="tcp:25772:64"/>
not able to plucke vs oute of theym? And that more is, will we make him a lyar, as though he wolde not kepe his promes that he made vnto vs, for to preſerue them that folowe his wayes? wherfore in ſteade of alledginge, what ſhall become of vs, yf we ſerue God, let vs learne to ſaye, ſeynge that all counſell doeth fayle vs, God hathe ſome other in ſtoore for vs. Are we in ſtraight / oute of the whiche we thinke there is no waye, to eſcape oute?</p>
            <p>Then will he make the waye wyder, onely let vs doo what oure Lorde God byddeth vs, and in what peryll ſo euer we be, he ſhall ſurely helpe vs.</p>
            <p>Aboue all thinge the lorde God
<pb facs="tcp:25772:65"/>
loueth this confydence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when we kepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, we do commit thende vnto his prouidence, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſpirite do quietly reſt vpon the ſame. But yf that a thouſande perylles do preſent them ſelues before our eyes in ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we knowe not whiche way to wynde vs: ſhall we therfore ſay, that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is in vaine, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take no more place? No, but we know that it ought not to be vyolate nor broken, though heauen and earth ſhold go together.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles, belly wiſdome wyll not that it be thus anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for ſhe obiecteth an other inconuenyence, that yf euerye man ſhoulde wythdrawe hym ſelfe from Idolatrye. Fyrſte all
<pb facs="tcp:25772:65"/>
landes where Antichriſt reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſhulde be deſtitute of faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full people. Secondarely, that when they be departed frome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where they were, they ſhoulde not knowe where to dwell, conſyderinge the regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s where God is purely called v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, can not holde them with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitauntes that be there al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redy. I anſwer, that this, feare is verye vayne, for yf that all they, whome our Lorde hathe illuminated, with one accorde and commune conſent, were ſo ſtronge rather for to dye or to leaue all togyther, then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyle them ſelues with wycked ſuperſtityons, he wolde helpe them by ſome meane that we know not of: for eyther he wold conuerte the hertes of the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:25772:66"/>
and of the Magiſtrates, &amp; moue them to put downe al I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye, and ſet vp the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice and worſhippinge of God, or els at the leaſt wolde molly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye them ſo, that they wold not conſtrayne the poore faithfull people for to defile them ſelues againſt their conſciences, nor vſe no more ſuche crueltye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Furthermore, that we enter no further in diſputa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, I ſaye that we ſhall not now doubt, that euery one will truſſe vp his baggage for to ſet forwarde. For alwayes thus will the worlde good, that ſome ſhall haue their eyes ſo blynded that they can not perceyue in what myre and fylthines they lye in: &amp; other, althoughe they do ſo, &amp; acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:25772:66"/>
eſtate wherein they be, ſhall neuertheles be hold in through the infirmite of the fleſhe for to abyde there ſtill. And ſome ſhal be ſo wrapped with dyuerſe ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res and burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can not auoyde it, al be it they wolde fayne do it.</p>
            <p>But it is very lykly (wil ſome man ſay) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei which haue the better zeale &amp; more knowledge for to edifye other, will go their waye: what will come of this then; how can the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goſpel be multiplied, yf the ſede be taken awaye? To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that yf euery one of them which be here and there, vnto whom oure Lorde hath geuen the knowledge of his truthe, dyd but the half of his dutie to
<pb facs="tcp:25772:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his power, that there ſhoulde not be one corner of the worlde which ſhould not be fylled ther with. The fault is, that there is no boldnes nor courage in the moſte parte, but yet althoughe all they that coulde not lyue in one Contrey wyth a quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, bycauſe they myght not lyue after Goddes worde, dyd departe away, thynke we that the ſeede of God ſhould vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be extyncte? We ſhoulde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope, that god in the ſtead of one, wolde rayſe vp fower. In concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ſhalbe alwaes fooles, ſo longe as we wyll rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſte God. I know alſo, that there be ſome which think to cleare them ſelues very wel by ſayenge, that it is an eayſye thyng for me to ſay thus ſeyng
<pb facs="tcp:25772:67"/>
I am far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daunger: but that if I were in their place, I wold not be ſo hotte, but wold do as they doo. I anſwere, that I ſay none other thyng, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whych my conſcience conſtrayneth me to ſpeake: and that, yf I wolde ſay other wiſe, I ſhould wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly blaſpheme the truth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if I were in a place where I thought that I ſhoulde not auoyd Idolatry without daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, I wold pray our lord, that he wolde ſtrengthen me: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde gyue me this conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy to prefarre (as reaſon requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) his glorye, before myne owne lyfe, &amp; I hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde not forſake me.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, let vs leaue to diſpute what I wolde do, for I do not boaſte my ſelfe: but do
<pb facs="tcp:25772:68"/>
onely ſhewe that, which as wel I my ſelf, as euery man ought to do. And therfore, whoſoeuer dyd otherwyſe (were it I my ſelfe or anye other) he were to be reproued. But what doth it helpe them for to loke vpon me If I do otherwyſe then I haue preached, wo be vnto me: for as moche as I ſhulde condempne my ſelfe by myne owne mouth. But are they therfore to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed? let euery body proue his owne worke,<note place="margin">Gala. 6.</note> ſaith S. Paule, and then he ſhall haue glory in him ſelfe and not in his neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, it is a very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune thing in the world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one doth make him a buckler for to defende hym ſelfe, by the faultes of an other, but a man maye not vſe thus for to do before God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:68"/>Furthermore, to the intente they ſhoulde not ſaye, theſe be wordes, but fynde me one (I praye you) that doth ſo. I requyre nothynge off theym, but to folowe that whyche ſo manye thouſande Martyres haue done before vs, men and Women, Ryche and Poore, greate and ſmall. This doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne then is no ſpeculation, that I haue inuented, euer the ſoner becauſe I my ſelfe am (as I and they do thynke) ſafe and well at eaſe / but it is the ſame whyche the holye Martyres of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte / haue occupyed theym ſelues wyth in the myddes of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that they ſuffered.</p>
            <p>And by thys medytation they were ſtrengthened &amp; holpen
<pb facs="tcp:25772:69"/>
to ouercome the dred and feare of priſonnes, of rackinge, of the fier, of the gallouſe, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweard, &amp; of all other kyndes of death. If they had not had thys tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly prynted in their hartes, that it were better for them to dye an hundred tymes, then to do any thynge agaynſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of God, they had neuer had the courage, to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vnto the death, for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the chriſtian faith: but they wolde rather haue ſuffered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be induced for to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Idolles</p>
            <p>Now, their conſcience is not recited vnto vs, onely bycauſe that we ſhoulde prayſe it: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it myght be an example to vs, and that we forſake not the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte whiche they dyd ſo manful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:25772:69"/>
maynteyne, that we do not ſet at naught, nor corrupte the glory of God whiche they eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo hyghely, that they ſhed their bloud for to ſeale and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrm it: yf thei had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought it lawful to eſcape by ſymulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or diſſemblynge, when men wold conſtrain them, to encline vnto Idolatry: then had it bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now no nede that they ſhoulde haue geuen ouer them ſelues, for to endure ſuch torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes as they ſuffered. For they myghte haue worſhipped God ſecretly, and made as thoughe they had worſhyſhypped Idols, for to ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfy their perſecuters with al. But they haue taught vs that that is nothynge elſe but moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage, to pretende that a man doth honoure God in hys hert,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:70"/>
when he betrayeth the truthe before men, and ſo defyleth his honoure by gyuinge it vnto I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles. And truelye when eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye thynge is well weyed, this is no ſmall condempnation v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs / for to ſee what an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente and a burnynge zeale the holy Martyrs hadde in tymes paſte in compariſon of the cold zeale that we ſhewe oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to haue, for by and by as ſoone as a poore man in thoſe dayes hadde but onelye a lytle taſte of the true knowledge oft God, he made no doubte to caſt him ſelfe in daunger, for the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of hys faythe / and had rather to be ſlayne quicke then to counterfayte or dyſſemble ſo moche, as to commytte an acte of anye outwarde Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye.
<pb facs="tcp:25772:70"/>
We that haue ſo greate knowledge, whiche ſhoulde ſet vs on fyer, be more colde then Iſe, and beſydes that, goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to excuſe or iuſtyfye oure ſelues. But yf we doo ſo, we ſhall heape vnto oure ſelues a more greuouſe curſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the ſorer, the wrathe of God vppon our headdes, and let euery man for his own part marke this diligently.</p>
            <p>Nowe euen as hytherto, I haue foughten agaynſte them whiche for to waſſhe and iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye them ſelues, doo falſifye the truthe of God, or for to extenu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate or mynyſh their faultes, do derogation vnto the maieſte of his word, and diminiſh thaucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or els y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by vayne clokes wold excuſe
<pb facs="tcp:25772:71"/>
themſelues, that it myghte be lawful for them, to do euyll, and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reproue them. So on thother ſyde, it is good reaſon to preuente the queſtion which many good perſonnes and ſuch as feare God myght happen to aſke, that is to wytte, whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I do reproue and condempne all the faythfull, whiche be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed thorow out Fraunce, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, Englande, Flaunders, and other Realmes: in as moch as (in many of theſe) they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to vſe many ſuperſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ceremonies. Before I an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere to this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I proteſt before God that ſo farre is it of that I do delyte to rebuke and reproue my poor brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be in ſuch captiuite, that rather for the pitie and compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
<pb facs="tcp:25772:71"/>
I haue vpon them, I wolde de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſe ſome way to excuſe them: but yet ſo, that I ſpeake as my conſcience doth compell me to ſay, yea, and that for their owne health. And after that I haue ſayd all, I do mourne for them, deſyryng God that he wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte them: touchyng the repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge of them, thys is not my mynde, where as I rebuke any vice in theym, therfore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne their perſonnes: God knoweth that I haue this eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of many that be diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed abrode, that they lyue moch more holyly than I do, and in greater perfection. Moreouer, I knowledge and conſider wel that it is a greatter and more excellent vertu for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kepe them ſelues in the feare of god,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in the myddes of ſuche of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than I which haue no ſuch occaſyon, and am not ſo moche tempted to do euell: but contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rywyſe haue dayely the worde of God to drawe me backe. In lykewyſe, yf they happen to fall that I ought to beare more w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, then I my ſelfe ought to be fauored or to be borne with. Therfore, ſo farre is it of, that I do reiecte them, as thoughe I ſhulde not take them for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: in that I do els laude &amp; prayſe them before God and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo before men, countinge them more worthy to haue a place in the churche of God than I: let vs ſet aſyde then this falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that I wolde exclude the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frome the nombre of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or compte them for no Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb facs="tcp:25772:72"/>
men.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, thoughe I haue their perſonnes in ſuche honoure and reputation, yet I ceaſe not (yf I ſee any vice in them) for to iudge it euyll: for althoughe a man be very faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, yet one can not ſaye, that all his workes be good and lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dable: it is poſſible they maye fynde other fautes in me, let theym condempne theym in the name of God: but let it not be of euell will or throughe the deſyre to diſprayſe or backbyte me, or for to reuenge them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues thorowe accuſynge me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. That notwithſtanding, let them receyue this correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with humblenes, yf they wil ſhewe theym ſelues to be the children of God: or elles they
<pb facs="tcp:25772:73"/>
ſhall declare them ſelues to be led wyth a ſpirite of rebellyon, and bytterneſſe: ſeynge that theye wolde not receyue the truthe.</p>
            <p>But one, wyll demaunde of me, what counſell then I wold gyue a faythfull perſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſo in ſome Egipt, or in ſom Babylon, in the which he is not ſuffered to worſhyp God puer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but is conſtrayned after the common faſſhyon to conforme hym ſelfe vnto euyll vſages.</p>
            <p>The fyrſt were, that he ſhold get hym from thence if he can, for all thynges well rekened &amp; debated, happy is he that is far from ſuche abhomynations, for as moche as it is verye harde to be ſo nyghe and not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyled wyth them. Let hym the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25772:73"/>
drawe hym ſelfe vnto the place where he ſhall not be conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to medle with ſuche fylthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: nor yet to blaſpheme the name of god, nor his worde, by holdynge his peace and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blynge as though he conſented on the other ſyde, where as he myght be ſuffered to make pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of his chriſtian faithe, in the aſſemble of chriſtian people, to be partaker of the holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of the goſpell, to haue the pure and wholſome vſe of the Sacraments, to haue his part of the common prayers.</p>
            <p>Here, haue ye my opynion, what were beſt to be done: but yf anye man fynde no waye to get oute, I wolde counſell hym to loke, whether it were not poſſyble for hym, to abſteyne
<pb facs="tcp:25772:74"/>
from all Idolatry, and to kepe hym ſelfe pure and vndefyled towarde God, as well in body, as in ſoule. Then, that he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped god priuately, deſiryng hym that he wyll reſtoore hys poore Churche vnto her ryght eſtate. Fynally, that he doo hys dilygence for to inſtructe and edyfye the poore Ignoraunte, as moch as he may: if he abiect that he can not do thys wyth out daunger of deth. I graunt it: but the glory of God where of we intreate now, oughte to be more precious vnto vs then this vayne and tranſitory lyfe whiche (to ſaye the truth) is nothyng but a ſhadow.</p>
            <p>I knowe, what the moſte parte wyll ſay vnto me, alas it is very truth that we ought to
<pb facs="tcp:25772:74"/>
prefer God before all thynges: but we haue no ſuche ſtrength nor conſtancy, where we haue father and mother whyche do retayn vs here, wher we haue charge of houſeholde, how can we well get awaye? Vnto this I ſay, for as moche as their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmytie doth let them, to folow the counſell whyche they doo acknowledge to be moſte ſure and healthful, that for as moch as for the feare of men they do bow from the ryght way, they oughte to confeſſe their ſynne before God: and wyth teares and ſyghes to bewayle it, accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge them ſelues in the ſteade of iuſtifyeng. Then, I do admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſſhe theym that by cuſtome they ſleape not in theyr euyll: but from daye to day, endeuer
<pb facs="tcp:25772:75"/>
them ſelues to myſlyke them ſelues and to be ſory, that they may obteyn mercy before god. Then, afterwarde to deſyre, their good father (for as moche as hys offyce is, to redeme pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoners) that he wyll once draw them out of bondage: or els pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare a ryght form of the church thorow oute all the world, that they may gyue hym the honor, that belongeth vnto hym. Fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, to ſeke all the wayes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble, to gette out of this myre, and this myſerable and curſed eſtate, where in they bee: and take thoſe ſame meanes which ſhalbe offered vnto them, that they may ſhew that it was for no hypocryſy, that they deſired of God delyuerance: yf all men wolde thus do their dyligence,
<pb facs="tcp:25772:75"/>
I doubte not, but that our lord wolde worke, otherwyſe then he dothe, for to deſtroy all abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynations and Idolatry, that raigne vpon the earthe. But bycauſe we fele not our myſery nor be not touched with it, as we oughte to be: but rather as indurate perſons, do not paſſe vpon the matter / it is no maruell, that he doth thus ſuffer vs, ſo long to corrupte, in our fylthines. It is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, if we do not bethink vs the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, that he wyll let vs roote altogether therein.</p>
            <byline>☞ Tranſlated by R.G.</byline>
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:76"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Matthew the .x. b</bibl>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer knowledgeth me be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore men, hym wyll I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg alſo before my father whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in heauen. But whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer denieth me before men, him wyll I alſo denie, before my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whiche is in heauen.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Romayns the .x. d</bibl>
                  <p>If thou knowledgeſt Ieſus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy mouth / that he is the lorde / and beleueſte in thine hert that God hathe rayſed hym from the dead thou ſhat be ſauid. For if a man beleue from the herte / he ſhall be made ryghtuous: &amp; yf a man knowledge wyth the mouth / he ſhall be ſaued. &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25772:76"/>
            <p>Imprinted at Ippyſwiche by me Ihon Oſwen the .x. daye of Auguſt.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad Imprimendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
